<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Attestation to the testimony of our reverend brethren of the province of London to the truth of Jesus Christ, and to our Solemn League and Covenant as also against the errours, heresies, and blasphemies of these times, and the toleration of them, resolved on by the ministers of Cheshire, at their meeting May 2, and subscribed at their next meeting, June 6, 1648.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26160</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17649</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12656605</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12656605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65388</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26160)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65388)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 341:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Attestation to the testimony of our reverend brethren of the province of London to the truth of Jesus Christ, and to our Solemn League and Covenant as also against the errours, heresies, and blasphemies of these times, and the toleration of them, resolved on by the ministers of Cheshire, at their meeting May 2, and subscribed at their next meeting, June 6, 1648.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 56, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Cotes for Christopher Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [10].</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65388:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ATTESTATION TO THE Teſtimony of our reverend Brethren of the Province of LONDON <hi>To the Truth of</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>and to our</hi> SOLEMN LEAGUE <hi>and</hi> COVENANT: <hi>AS ALSO,</hi> Againſt the Errours, Hereſies, and Blaſphemies of theſe Times, and the Toleration of them. Reſolved on by the Miniſters of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> at their meeting <hi>May</hi> 2. and ſubſcribed at their next Meeting, <hi>June</hi> 6. 1648.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame things; and that there be no diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgment,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 1.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Sunt qui quod ſentiant etiamſi optimum ſit, tamenn invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae metu non audent dicere,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicer. de Offic. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 362. <hi>edit. Lutet.</hi> 1554.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Patiemúrne igitur extingui aut opprimi veritatem ego verò libentius, vel ſub hoc onere defecerim,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lact. de Opificio Dei, c.</hi> 21. <hi>p.</hi> 808. <hi>edit. Lugdun.</hi> 1594.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in Pauls-church-yard, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:65388:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65388:2"/>
            <head>AN ATTESTATION Of the MINISTERS of CHESHIRE, To the <hi>TESTIMONY</hi> of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren of the Province of <hi>London,</hi> TO THE <hi>Truth of JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> And to our Solemn League and Covenant. <hi>As alſo,</hi> Againſt <hi>ERRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RS,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend and Well-beloved Brethren,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE cannot but apprehend it as an eſpeciall providence of God, that ſo many godly and faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt in the Countrey, (partly drawn together by authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to make up the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and partly driven to <hi>London,</hi> as to a City of refuge, for ſafety and ſuccour from the violence and outrage of the adverſe party) have been lawfully allowed, and have frequently injoyed, many opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for <hi>communication</hi> of <hi>counſells,</hi> and <hi>contribution</hi> of <hi>indeavours,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:65388:3"/>to carry on the Covenanted Reformation towards an happy conclution, <hi>which</hi> are like to be fruſtrate of much of the fruit and good effect deſired by them unleſſe there be a conſciencious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of your other brethren, who upon the ſame prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and intereſts ſtand deeply ingaged with you earneſtly to <hi>contend for the faith which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi> as juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is offered to ſhew themſelves not only reſolute <hi>Proteſtants</hi> for it, but religious <hi>Deteſtants</hi> againſt all errors, hereſies, and blaſphemies which are contrary to it.</p>
               <p>Wherein though you have <hi>precedency before us,</hi> and <hi>advantage above us</hi> (both for intelligence and accommedation of conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and conſequently for conſultation, conſent and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of what you reſolve on) we meant (at leaſt ſome of us, from the firſt view of your printed <hi>Teſtimony to the Truth of Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) you ſhould <hi>not therein bee ſingular without us.</hi> And now all of us whoſe names are ſubſcribed, doe freely and publickly profeſſe, both <hi>how far,</hi> and <hi>upon what grounds and reaſons,</hi> we give our Atteſtation to the contents of your booke forementioned: and firſt <hi>how far</hi> wee doe it, and for that,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, We wel like the latitude of your generall Title, in that it ſpeaks againſt <hi>errours, hereſies, and blaſphemies,</hi> and for that in the particular Titles all along your booke, you uſe the word errour only, and adde not the other words, hereſie, and blaſphemy, though many of the poſitions recited by you, be materially both hereticall and blaſphemous: wherein wee conceive you have been diſcreetly cautelous to prevent exception, for there is great doubt, much diſpute and difficultie, to determine <hi>what hereſie is,</hi> and what opinion is hereticall. Thence it is that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiph. An. <hi>370.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ephanius,</hi> and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Phil. An. <hi>380.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Philaſtrius</hi> (who both of them wrote of hereſies before<note n="(c)" place="margin">Aug. An. <hi>420.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) agree not in their Catalogue, for the one accounts thoſe tenents to be hereſies which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth not. And that<note n="(d)" place="margin">Bellarm. de Chriſto, lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> Tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>132, 133.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth acquit <hi>Calvin</hi> from the hereſie charged upon him by <hi>Genebrard,</hi> for teaching that Chriſt is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But though it may be queſtioned of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, whether they be <hi>hereſies</hi> or no, it may bee manifeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that they be <hi>errours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, We approve, that you paſſe your conſine upon hereſies <hi>in</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65388:3"/>
                  <hi>abſtract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> as <hi>Epiphanius, Philaſtrius, Auguſtine,</hi> &amp; <hi>Alphonſus à Caſtro,</hi> not upon Hereticks <hi>in Concret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> as<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Adverſus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus temporis hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticos, Bell.</hi> in title page of his diſputations.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles his diſputations not againſt the Hereſies but <hi>the Hereticks</hi> of <hi>theſe times.</hi> For that is farre more difficult to determine then the other. <hi>What makes an Hereticke cannot as I conceive at all, or very hardly be comprehended in a regular definition,</hi> ſaid<note n="(f)" place="margin">Quid facit haereticum regulari qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam definitione comprehendi (ſicut ego exiſtimo) aut omnino non poteſt, aut difficillime p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teſt. Aug. de Haereſ. ad quod vult Deum, Tom. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> many a hundred yeers agoe. The modern <hi>Arminians</hi> ſay as much or more, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Sciri hodie non poſſe quis ſit haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus—<hi>So the</hi> Arminians, Apud Nicol. Vedel. part. <hi>4.</hi> defenſ. Arcani Armin. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that it cannot be knowne in theſe times who is an Heretick:</hi> but they are the leſſe to be beleeved becauſe of more light in latter times, for the diſcovery of truth and error, then in the ages more remote. Yet is there great difficultie, and (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof) there may bee much deceit and errour, in an inconſiderate application of the word, <hi>Hereticke,</hi> though to a man of erroneous opinion, yea though groſſely erroneous.</p>
               <p>This difficultie was the cauſe that ſome of the Antients, who wrote againſt Hereticks were numbred with Hereticks them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as<note n="(h)" place="margin">Bellarmine <hi>in effect calls</hi> Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian <hi>heretick, when he ſaith</hi> Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianum inter Catholicos non numera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Bellarm. de poenit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Tom. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>377.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Epiphan. Haereſ. <hi>64. &amp; in a Synod of</hi> Alexandria. an. <hi>399</hi> vide Fran. Long. ſum. concil. p. <hi>324. and 325.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Origen;</hi> and that ſome of thoſe who wrote of hereſies ſince them have<note n="(k)" place="margin">Bernard Lutzenburg miſere erraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe qui Catalogum Haereticorum deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens aliquos recenſet qui nunquam in fide catholica fuerunt. Alphon. a caſtro Adverſus haereſ lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> f. <hi>23.</hi> p. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> (as <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro</hi> writeth of <hi>Bernard Lutzenburg</hi>) <hi>bren miſerably miſtaken in taking thoſe for hereticks who were not,</hi> and ſo came<note n="(l)" place="margin">Epiphan. haereſ. <hi>75.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aerius</hi> to be liſted in the black-bill of heretickes for denying <hi>the diſtinction betwixt a Biſhop and a Presbyter.</hi> And for the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (in kind, though differing in degree) was<note n="(m)" place="margin">Marc. Anton. De Dom. Spalat. de repub. Eccleſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>240.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> taken for an <hi>Aerian</hi> Hereticke by <hi>Michael Medina,</hi> but fooliſhly and ignorantly ſaith the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Deſeruimus in hac parte Hieronym: Sed non propterea ſtulte &amp; imperite (quod facit Michael Medina) illum Hereticum facimus Aerianum. M. Anton. de Dom. Arch. Spalat. ubi ſupra.</note> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Spalat.</hi> And for <hi>Aerius</hi> himſelfe (though hee denied not only the Divine: right of Epiſcopall prelation, which <hi>Hierom</hi> did) but all right of preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of Biſhops over Presbyters in the Church, (which <hi>Hierom</hi> did not) he is cleared alſo from that contumelious title by the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned author of the book called<note n="(o)" place="margin">Altar. Damaſc. p. <hi>276. 277, 279</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Altare Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65388:4"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Our judgements and deſires concur with yours, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the humble advice of the Aſſembly of Divines, now by authority of Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> concerning a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, whereof we conceive it needleſſe, to ſay any more, or otherwiſe then you have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, We profeſſe we are filled with griefe for the preſent evills upon us, and with fear of worſe (which ſeem eminent over us) for want of that Church Government, which is moſt agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the word of God, and to the example of the beſt reformed Churches, and we are ſo much the more afflicted with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of both, becauſe the Ordinance of Parliament (for the eſtabliſhment of it in a regular ſubordination of <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, Claſſicall,</hi> and <hi>Provinciall</hi> Presbyterie's) prevaileth ſo little in moſt places; which we muſt impute partly to the miſrepreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it, to thoſe that ſhould ſubmit unto it; (for to ſome it is rendred <hi>formidable</hi>) as if it were more oppreſſive then ever the Prelacie was; to others <hi>deſpicable,</hi> for want of a competent power to proceed to effectuall reformation of offenders; and to moſt (whatſoever it be in it ſelf) it is the more unwelcome, becauſe they have bin ſo long wonted to live without rule, that now as ſons of<note n="(p)" place="margin">Belial a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Beli,</hi> id eſt non, &amp; nomine <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ol,</hi> id eſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum, ut ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur impatien tia jugi, id eſt diſciplinae. Mr. Leigh crit. Sacr. in N. T. p. <hi>43.</hi> Margin.</note> 
                  <hi>Belial</hi>) having ſhaken off the yoak of ſubjection, they take it for an injury if any reſtraint be offered to their licentious humors, Which ſome by a partiall <hi>Charientiſmus</hi> miſ-call by the name of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience, whither</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> well obſerveth) <hi>the Devill ſometimes flyes</hi> (<hi>as</hi> Joab <hi>did</hi>) <hi>to the hornes of the Altar, or ſeems to doe ſo, when if he be well ſought for, you ſhall find him in ſome other roome of the ſoule (as in the will) but he pretends to conſcience; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to eſcape there better then any where elſe.</hi> And as the Civill and Eccleſiaſticall Government, when they are reciprocally authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, are both a ſupport and reputation to each other;<note n="q" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs</hi> his <hi>Iren. p.</hi> 29, 30.</note> ſo we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſadly forecaſt how much the Civil power will bee caſt downe, at leaſt enfeebled and contemned, if ſome Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall awe bee not put upon the Spirits of the people, as well by order of Diſcipline as rule of Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, For the Solemn League and Covenant (as it is called in the Title of it) ſo gravely and piouſly penned, ſo dreadfully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging the conſcience, (in all ſincerity and fidelity, to take and keepe it) ſo ratified by Authority of Parliament, (ordering the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65388:4"/>taking of it with inſtructions, exhortations and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuch ſcruples as might ariſe about it, and that it ſhould thus bee publiſhed in all the Churches of <hi>England,</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales;</hi> with the moſt ſolemne ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of it, by the Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, and the Aſſembly of Divines, after a divine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of it, and preparation for it in the Pulpit. That this ſo Solemne League and Covenant ſhould bee by ſo many with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſenſe of Religion both taken and broken, as if it were but as a King at Cheſſe ſet upon the board for a game, and to be ſhut up in the bagge, (when the game is done) this is that which may make us to hang down our heads, with heavy hearts, and with <hi>Ezra</hi> each of us to ſay, <hi>O my God I am aſhamed and bluſh to lift up my face to thee my God, for our ſinnes are increaſed over our heads, and our treſpaſſe is growne up unto heaven, Ezra</hi> 9.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, From our Religious conſent with you in theſe three <hi>(the Confeſſion of Faith, Government of the Church, and Solemn League and Covenant)</hi> wil neceſſarily follow our hearty and ſerious dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of <hi>Errours, Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies</hi> and the <hi>Toleration</hi> of them; which are deſtructive to all three; and though as Errors &amp;c. they bee all one in the malignant and miſchievous end, they ayme: yet in their way to that end, they are capable of diſtinct and different conſideration, both for the Errours, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Blaſphemies themſelves, and for the toleration of them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then, for the Errours, &amp;c. as you have ſorted them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeverall Titles, ſo have you fitted your titles with anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſtances and pregnant proofes, beſides and without ſuch particulars as are capable of ſome problematicall debate, and by their conformity to ſome obſcure Scripture phraſe, may (at laſt) by diſtinction and limitation bee like to take ſanctuary in a Scripture ſenſe, though there bee no reaſon, why men who are ſubject unto errour, and many times doe erre, ſhould have their ambiguous expreſſions entertained with ſo faire and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable a conſtruction, as the Word of God, which cannot erre, and which if it be obſcure in one place, gives light for its own clearing and interpretation in another.</p>
               <p>Beſides, of this wee are bound to take notice, becauſe wee are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65388:5"/>bidden to ſearch the Scriptures, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39. all the Scriptures, <hi>for all Scripture is of Divine inſpiration, and profitable, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. But for humane writings we are not obliged to be ſo well acquainted with them, nor to have ſo much reſpect unto them.<note n="r" place="margin">Luther. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> in Gen. p. <hi>144.</hi> operùm lenae excuſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Luther</hi> was once ſo far carryed with a pleonaſm of zealous emulation of the honor &amp; utility of the Word of God (above the writings of men) that he wiſh't his own Books were burn't, for fear they ſhould be an hinderance to men's more profitable employment in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Scriptures; though otherwiſe hee was wiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to know how ſerviceable handmaids to Divinity they may bee, if deſcreetly uſed; and for his own workes<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Ad eruditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, &amp; ſapienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am illam Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae peculiarem, &amp; mundo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, de gratia Dei &amp; juſtitia fidei intelligend. plus conducit unicus Lutherus in Ep. ad Galat. quam omnia Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eronymi, Baſi lii, Cyrilli, Origenis, Naz Epiph. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larii &amp; plera<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> patrum opera in unum collecta. David. Chytraeus de ſtud Theol. fol. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>whereof ſome</hi> (for ſpirituall proficiency) <hi>are preferred before many Volumes of the Fathers,</hi> hee ſhewed himſelfe ſo addicted to them, that when by the Popes decree his bookes were burnt,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Sleid. Com. l. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>39.</hi> V. Nihilo plus ſanctitatis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe Scripturis, quam caudae ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninae aut felinae. <hi>See Mr.</hi> Vicars <hi>his Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Coleman-ſtreet conclave viſited, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and proof of it.</hi> pag. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> hee <hi>in revenge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> ſolemnly burnt the Popes Lawes and that papall decree, upon which ſo ſevere a ſentence, and execution paſſed upon them.</p>
               <p>From his high eſtimation of theſe ſacred Oracles how low are they fallen in this wretched generation of our's, when ſome have not been aſhamed nor afraid, (which in the uttering, and hearing, wee thinke worthy to bee entertained with the <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the belly and quivering of the lips</hi> of the Prophet <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.16.) blaſphemouſly to compare <hi>them in point of holyneſſe to the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible part of the meaneſt creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee could (under other titles) make remarkable additions to your Catalogue of errours, of our own times, (as your ſelves wee doubt not might eaſily have done) but that bundle of weeds is ſufficient for the preſent (having occaſion under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother title to bring in many others) to ſhew how negligently the garden of the Lord hath been kept, and how ſubtilly and ſucceſſefully Satan hath proceeded in his ſeducements of ſimple and ſinfull people. And therefore as wee profeſſe we are deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with fear and ſorrow, for the prevailings of Satan ſo farr a mong us: ſo in the next place we cannot but zealouſly avow our diſlike of Toleration of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65388:5"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>BUt here we crave leave clearly to deliver what in judgment and conſcience wee conceive and doe deſire for this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
               <p>Firſt, We think it meet that a due diſtinction be made betwixt errour and errour, becauſe <hi>Humanum eſt errare,</hi> and wiſh that (ſince all men never were nor will bee of one and the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, no more then of the ſame feature and complextion) it were diligently debated, and judiciouſly reſolved what is the latitude of allowable differences by the Word of God, and how farre the ſtrong ought to beare with the infirmities of the weak, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the lives of erroneous Dogmatiſts (though civil or religious) ſhould not gain ſo much credit or countenance to any dangerous or damnable tenet, as to procure it favour, or protection, for their ſakes. For a very erroneous Religion may have ſome that profeſſe it ſuch as may be commendable for their morall converſation. And though<note n="(w)" place="margin">Sunt quidem in Eccleſia Catholica plurimi mali, ſed ex haereticis nullus eſt bonus. Bellarm. de not. Eccleſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi> Tom. p. p. <hi>83.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> out of hatred to thoſe hee calls Hereticks (and hee thinkes moſt of Proteſtants when hee uſeth that name) ſay <hi>that among Catholiques</hi> (that is, Papiſts, in his dialect) <hi>there bee many bad, but of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks there be none good,</hi> wee doubt not to aver the contrary with<note n="(x)" place="margin">Multi qui a perte foris ſunt &amp; haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici appellantur, multis &amp; bonis Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis meliores ſunt. Aug. de baptiſm. contra Donat. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tom. <hi>7.</hi> part. <hi>1.</hi> pag. <hi>503.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> who ſaith, <hi>many of thoſe who are without and called he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, are better then thoſe who with us are held good Catholickes:</hi> and wee may ſay the like of Papiſts, Turkes, yea of heathens, and particularly of (that Sect which is moſt licentious) the <hi>Epicures</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Epicurus bonus vir fuit &amp; multi E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picurei fuerunt &amp; hodie ſunt in amicitia fideles &amp; in omni vita conſtantes &amp; graves. Ita vivunt quidam ut corum vita probetur, refellitur oratio. At ut<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri exiſtimantur melius dicere quam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſic hi mihi videntur facere melius quam dicere. Cicer. de finib. bonorum &amp; malorum lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>65.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith that <hi>Epicurus the author of it was a good man, and many Epicureans were and to this day are faithfull in friendſhip, in the whole courſe of their lives conſtant, grave; Some of them ſo live that their life is approved, while their ſpcech is worthy to be refuted: and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65388:6"/>as others are obſerved to ſay better then they doe, ſo theſe doe ſeeme to doe better then they ſay.</hi> If then the lifes of ſeducing Teachers, bee alleadged to get approbation of their doctrine; we muſt ſay as was ſaid unto <hi>Torquatus,</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">Non quaeritur quid naturae tuae conſentanewn, ſed quid diſciplinae, Cicer. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>the matter in queſtion is not what is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to thy diſpoſition, but what to the diſcipline or inſtruction of others,</hi> not how good the Doctor is, but how ſound the doctrine he divulgeth, &amp; if the one be good, the other bad, in ſuch a caſe, the ſaying of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Diligite homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, interficite err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res, Aug. contra lit. Pet Donat. l. <hi>1.</hi> prope fin. p. <hi>104.</hi> Tam. <hi>7.</hi> part. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is ſeaſonable and ſutable to both, deal in all mildneſſe with the men, but ſhew no mercy to their errour.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, For the errors of men if they be ſuch as be not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to the Scripture, but inconſiſtent with ſalvation, both Miniſters and Magiſtrates (we ranke them thus, not in order of dignity but of duty) may and ought according to their callings and places to oppoſe them; ſo that they may ſuppreſſe them: 1. Miniſters by diſcovering of them, preaching, writing, and diſputing againſt them, as the quality of the errour ſhall require: for ſome doctrines of Religion are ſuch ſundamentall Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as ought to be priviledged from diſpute, which<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rem, meaſententia minime dubiam, argumentando dubiam facias, Cicer. de nat. Deorum. l. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>243.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>though they be moſt certain may be made doubtfull by ſophisticall wranglings,</hi> and ſome er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour (as that of<note n="(c)" place="margin">Anaxagoras dixit nivem eſſe ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram. Cicer. Acad. qu. lin. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> who held <hi>ſnow was black,</hi> and that of<note n="(d)" place="margin">Inter optime valere &amp; graviſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me aegrotare Ariſto &amp; Pyrrho dixerunt nihil intereſſe. Cicero de fin. Bon. &amp; Mal. lin. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>58.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ariſto &amp; Pyrrho,</hi> whoſe opinion was that there <hi>was no difference between very good health and grievous ſickneſſe,</hi> and that of<note n="(e)" place="margin">Aliud Iudicium Protagerae, eſt qui putet id cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> verum eſſe quod cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatur. Cicer. Acad. qu. lin. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Protagoras</hi> who thought that <hi>that is true to every one, which appeareth or ſeemeth to bee true</hi>) are ſo abſurd, that they are more worthy to bee exploded then deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any argument of reaſon, and <hi>againſt ſuch</hi> (ſaith the<note n="f" place="margin">Cicer. de finib. ubi ſupra lit. d.</note> Oratour,) <hi>men have long ſince left off to diſpute;</hi> and ſuch ſurely are many of the fanaticall fancies of our preſent time.</p>
               <p>But ſuch Tenents as may deſerve diſpute, and may ſafely be admitted to debate and diſcuſſion, (though occaſionally both Miniſters and other Chriſtians may fall to argument and conteſtation about them) wee conceive (and thereupon have unanimouſly reſolved for our ſelves,) that no ſet conference or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65388:6"/>diſpute concerning them bee undertaken by any Miniſter or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther private Chriſtian, without the common conſent of the Miniſters, and their advice how to order or manage it in the moſt convenient manner. And ſecondly, for Magiſtrates, we hold it to be their duty, (and they are to be put in mind of it by the Miniſters if need require) to prohibit the publiſhing or ſpreading of falſe and dangeroùs opinions, and if they bee publiſhed in Bookes and Pamphlets, that they ought to purſue them, with zeale as hot as fire, that they may bee burned as the Bookes of<note n="(g)" place="margin">Abderites Protagoras cum in principi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri ſui ſic poſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet de Diis ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ut ſint, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ut non ſint, habeo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. — libri ejus in concione combuſti ſunt Cicer. de Nat. Deo. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>206.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Abderites Protagoras</hi> were at <hi>Athens</hi> for his ſpeaking <hi>doubtfully of Religion in the beginning of them,</hi> and the bookes <hi>of curious arts at Epheſus, Acts</hi> 19.19. and the Bookes of <hi>the hereticks,</hi> as of<note n="(h)" place="margin">Nicep. Caliſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> Eccl. Hiſt. c. <hi>18.</hi> col. <hi>384.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Arius</hi> and others, and that the perſons of ſuch as are forward to poyſon ſoules with pernicious errours, if when they be forbidden they will not forbeare, ought either to be confined, or exiled, a<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
                  <note n="(i)" place="margin">Athen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſium juſſu urbe at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> agro extermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt libri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ejus ut ſupra ad lirt. g.</note> 
                  <hi>Abderites Protagoras was by the Civill authority,</hi> and no more to be allowed liberty to ſeduce the ſoules of men to the belief of damnable doctrines, then thoſe who have the Plague ſore running upon them to come into all companies, or for furious mad men to bee permitted to walke at large with Swords in their hands to wound and kill whom they meet, if they have a mind unto it.</p>
               <p>And wee take it to bee the true <hi>Bloody Tenent,</hi> (which might give denomination to the Booke of that title, (though the Authour meant no ſuch matter)<note n="k" place="margin">Bloody Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, <hi>p.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>That it is the will of God that ſince the comming of his Son Chriſt Ieſus, a permiſsion of the moſt Pagan, Iewiſh, Turkiſh, and Antichriſtian conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and worſhips be granted to all men, in all Nations and Countries, and that they are onely to bee fought againſt, (with that which onely in ſoule matters is able to conquer) to wit, the ſword of Gods Spirit, the Word of God. And</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Ibid. c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that to moleſt any perſon, Iew or Gentile, for either profeſsing doctrine or practiſing Worſhip meerely Religious or Spirituall, is to perſecute him, and ſuch a perſon what ever his Doctrine or practice bee, true or falſe, ſuffers the perſecution for conſcience.</hi> Which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65388:7"/>are ſuch maximes of ſoule-murther as if when hee wrote them, Satan (who moſt thirſteth for the blood of ſouls) did not onely ſtand at his right hand, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. but did guide his pen while he wrote ſuch paradoxes of perdition, againſt which it were an eaſie taske, (if it were any part of our preſent undertaking) to make good the contrary tenent of<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mea primitus Sententia erat nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ad veritatem Chriſti eſſe cogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. Sed haec opinio mea—non contradicentium verbis ſed demonſtrantium ſuperabatur exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis. Aug. Ep. <hi>48.</hi> Vincentio p. <hi>195.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine; Where hee corrected his former remiſneſſe and lenity towards the erronious by reſolving upon better conſideration, that men may be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to their own good, and overruled when they are in an evill mind, which is the ſummary contents of his Epiſtle to Donatus the Donatiſt, when cited to the councell hee offered to make away himſelfe by the way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, In oppoſition to the prodigious indulgence forenoted and to the evill effects it may produce (if not oppoſed by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates as well as by the Miniſters.) We conceive it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the High Court of Parliament to ſet forth an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the puniſhing of Blaſphemies,<note n="n" place="margin">The ſame day the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> met at <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved of an Atteſtation to the Teſtimony to the truth of Jeſus Chriſt. &amp;c.</note> as they did the ſecond of <hi>May,</hi> 1648. Whereof the ſummary Contents which wee think meet to mention in this place are, <hi>that all ſuch perſons as ſhall from and after the date of this preſent Ordinance willingly by preaching, teaching, printing or writing, maintain and publiſh that there is no God, or that God is not preſent in all places, doth not know and foreknow all things, or that hee is not Almighty, that he is not perfectly Holy, or that he is not Eternall, or that the Father is not God, the Son is not God or that the Holy Ghoſt is not God: or that ſhall in like manner maintaine and publiſh, that Chriſt is not God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with the Father, or ſhall deny the manhood of Chriſtor that the Godhead and Manhood of Chriſt are ſeverall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or that the humanity of Chriſt is pure and unſpotted from all ſinne, or that ſhall maintain or publiſh as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that Chriſt did not dye, nor riſe from the dead, nor is aſcended into heaven bodily, or that deny his death is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65388:7"/>meritorious in the behalfe of Beleevers: or that ſhall maintain and publiſh as aforeſaid, that the holy Scriptures of the Old Teſtament from the firſt of</hi> Geneſis <hi>to</hi> Malachi, <hi>and of the New Teſtament from</hi> Matthew <hi>to the</hi> Revelation <hi>is not the Word of God; or that the bodies of men ſhall not riſe againe, or that there is no day of Iudgement after death: All ſuch maintaining and publiſhing of ſuch errour or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours is made felony, and the party accuſed thereof by the oath of two witneſſes before any two of the next Iuſtices, (who in ſuch a caſe are authorized by the Ordinance, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter an Oath) or by confeſſion of the party ſhall by them bee committed to priſon without baile or mainprize untill the next Gaole-delivery at which hee ſhall bee indicted for felonious publiſhing and maintaining ſuch errour. And in caſe the Indictment bee found, and the party upon his triall ſhall not abjure his ſaid errour and defence, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the ſame, hee ſhall ſuffer the paines of death, as in caſe of felonie without benefit of Clergie, and in caſe hee ſhall renounce and abjure his &amp;c. Hee ſhall nevertheleſſe remaine in priſon untill hee ſhall find two ſureties (being ſubſidy men) that hee ſhall not thenceforth publiſh, &amp;c. And if after abjuration hee relapſe and it bee proved as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, hee ſhall ſuffer death as in caſe of Felony without benefit of Clergy. And it is further Ordained by authority aforeſayd, that every perſon that ſhall publiſh or maintain as aforeſaid, that all men ſhall bee faved; or that man by nature hath free will to turn to God; or that God may bee worſhipped in or by pictures or Images; or that the ſoule of any man after death goeth neither to heaven or hell, but to Purgatory; or that the ſoule of man dyeth or ſleepeth when the body is dead; or that Revelations or the workings of the Spirit are a rule of faith or Chriſtian life though diverſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65388:8"/>from or contrary to the written word of God; or that man is bound to beleeve no more then by his reaſon he can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend; or that the Morall law of God contained in the ten Commandements is no rule of Chriſtian life; or that a beleever need not repent or pray for pardon of ſinnes; or that the two Sacraments of Baptiſme and the Lords-ſupper are not Ordinances commanded by the word of God; or that the baptizing of Infants is unlawfull, or ſuch baptiſme is void, and that ſuch perſons ought to be baptized again, and inpurſuance thereof, ſhall baptize any perſon formerly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; or that the obſervation of the Lords day, as it is enjoyned by the Ordinances and Lawes of this Realm, is not according, or is contrary to the word of God; or that it is not lawfull to joyn in publick prayer, or family prayer, or to teach children to pray; or that the Churches of</hi> England <hi>are not true Churches, nor their Miniſters and Ordinances true Miniſters and Ordinances; or that the Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Presbytery is Antichriſtian or unlawfull; or that the Magiſtracy, or power of the civill Magiſtrate by law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in</hi> England, <hi>is unlawfull; or that all uſe of Armes, though for the publick defence, (and be the cauſe never ſo juſt) is unlawfull; and in caſe the party accuſed of ſuch publiſhing and maintaining of any ſuch errours ſhall bee convicted as aforeſaid, he ſhall be ordered by the ſaid Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to renounce his ſaid errors in the publick congregation of the ſame pariſh from whence the complaint doth come; and in caſe he refuſeth ſo to doe, then he ſhall be committed to priſon by the ſaid Iuſtices, untill hee find two ſufficient ſuretyes, that he ſhall not publiſh or maintain the ſaid error or errors any more.</hi> With this Proviſo, <hi>that no attainder by vertue hereof, ſpall extend either to the forfeiture of the eſtate reall or perſonall, or the corruption of blood of any ſuch perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65388:8"/>
               <p>Fifthly, Though we acknowledge divers of our brethren of the <hi>Independent</hi> way, to be learned, godly, charitable and kind even to their <hi>Presbyterian</hi> brethren, (and<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mr. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs in his Iren. cap. 6. p 30, 32, 34, 35 36, 37.</note> ſome of them to be adverſe in a great meaſure to ſuch a Toleration as<note n="*" place="margin">Teſt. to the truth, &amp;c. p. 29.</note> you might truely terme intolerable and abuminable, which that Catholick Advocate and Patron<note n="(p)" place="margin">In his booke called the Bloody Tenet.</note> of all irreligious Religions propoſeth) yet as we take the tenet of <hi>Independency</hi> to be an error in it ſelfe, ſo doe we find it by ſound reaſon and ſad experience to bee, if not the naturall mother, yet ſuch a tender Nurſe and Patroneſſe to hereticall opinions of all kinds, that to it we may (for a great part) aſcribe the luxuriant growth and ſpreading of errors, hereſies, &amp;c. ſo far over this Kingdome: as on the contrary the freedome of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> from the like evills<note n="(q)" place="margin">Eccleſ. Scotican. privilegium rarum in quo ejus nomen apud exteros fuit celebre, quod circiter annos, plus minus <hi>54.</hi> (ante an. <hi>1602.</hi>) ſine ſchiſina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e nedum haer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem cum puritate doctrinae retinuerit, in prin Syntag. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſeſſ. p. <hi>6.</hi> edit. Gen. <hi>1612.</hi> in <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> (which is recorded as their happineſſe and to their honour) to the firme eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of a ſubordinate Presbyteriall Government among them.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Notwithſtanding we are far from the rigorous reſolution of<note n="(r)" place="margin">Haeretices incorrigibiles &amp; poſſe &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere temporalibus paenis, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>que <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiam mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e muliart. Bell. de Laicis, l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, who is peremptorie for the puniſhment of heretickes with death</hi> (without any ſuch diſtinction or difference as is made in the Ordinance of Parliament)<note n="(s)" place="margin">Haere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icis obſtinatis beneficium eſt quod de hac vita tollantur, nam quod diutius vivunt, eo plures errores excogitant, plures perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt, &amp; majorem ſibi damnationem acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. ibid. p. <hi>225.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming alſo it is a kindneſſe to them, to cut them off; becauſe the longer they live, the more er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they will invent, the more perſons they will pervert, and ſo to procure themſelves the deeper damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which concluſion of his we account the more cruel, becauſe of the large extent of the title Heretick, in his ſenſe comprehending all Chriſtians who profeſſe not ſubjection to his Antichriſtian <hi>Caiphas</hi> the Pope. But we conceive the Spirit of Chriſt brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth into his, more meekneſſe and moderation towards ſuch as are contrary minded, though their ſimplicity have ſometime been ſo far wrought upon by the ſubtilty of others as<note n="(t)" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dicamenta neſciunt &amp; inſani ſunt adverſus Antidotum quo ſani eſſe potuiſſent. Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>262. 263.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to become mad againſt the medicine that ſhould cure them of their madneſſe.</hi> At whom when wee are moved to bee angry, wee muſt turne anger into pity as<note n="(u)" place="margin">Quam vehemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i &amp; aeri dolore indignabar Manichaeis &amp; miſerabar e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Aug. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65388:9"/>did towards the Manchichees,</hi> and when we oppoſe them, wee muſt as he<note n="(w)" place="margin">Sine ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia de veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate praeſumi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e: ſine ſaevitia pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue certa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. Aug. contra lit. Petil. Donatiſtae lib. <hi>1.</hi> Tom. <hi>7.</hi> par. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>104.</hi>
                  </note> adviſeth <hi>without pride preſume of the truth, and without cruelty contend for the truth,</hi> not abridging them of any liberty ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of opinion or of practiſe, which may be proved by the word of God to be a part of their Chriſtian right. Which we profeſſe without all prejudice to ſuch neceſſary and ſalutary ſeverity, as by juſt and lawfull authority is already or hereafter ſhall bee thought meet to be exerciſed upon thoſe, who by their ſedulity in ſolliciting to perillous opinions, as by their obſtinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in them may deſerve that.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>THus far for the firſt point, <hi>how farre you have our conſent.</hi> We are next to ſhew our reaſons why we thus joyn with you, both in our judgments and in our publick profeſſion thereof to the world. For though we thinke with <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Plurimum prodeſt unicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ique bono jungi. Ambr. de Offic. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi> princ.</note> that <hi>it is matter of advantage to ſort and aſſociate our ſelves to every good man,</hi> much more to ſo many and ſo worthy Divines as are united in your ſubſcription to the Teſtimony to the Trtuth, &amp;c. Yet we conceive it will be rather a ſupport to the cauſe, then a prejudice to you, or in us, to any other (who have appeared in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance before us (and who might bee ſo much ſhorter, as they were quicker in their Atteſtation) if we put off the reproof of<note n="(y)" place="margin">Sapientiam ſibi adimunt qui fine ullo judicio inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum probant &amp; ab aliis pecudum more ducuntur. Lactant. Inſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>139.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lactantius,</hi> by ſubjoyning to our former Aſſent ſuch confidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reaſons thereof as theſe that follow.</p>
               <p>The firſt we take from the juſt zeale we ought to bear to the glory of God, which is much oppoſed by error, herefies, and blaſphemies, and the Toleration of them. For albeit<note n="(z)" place="margin">Socr. c. hol. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>336.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtius</hi> told the Emperour <hi>Valens, that variety of Sects tended to the glory of God, though they amounted to more then</hi> 300, <hi>as did the opinions of the Philoſophers;</hi> God is jealous of honour, and as hee is but one, ſo he allowes but of one Lord, one faith, and one baptiſme, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.5. and being moſt true and holy, he cannot but be vehemently incenſed againſt errors, hereſies, and blaſphemies, eſpecially when they are preſented under the name and notion of Religion, for then he is twice diſhonoured. Firſt, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting his truth by falſhood, his glory by reproach; and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65388:9"/>then in aſcribing erroneous and hereticall opinions unto him as to the author of them, whereas indeed they are the dictates of the Devill. For as<note n="(a)" place="margin">Videns Diabolus templa de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum deſeri, &amp; in nomen Liberatoris, eurrere genus humanum; haereticos movit, qui ſub vocabulo Chriſtiano Doctrinae reſiſterent Chriſtianae. Aug. de Civit. Dei. l. <hi>8,</hi> c. <hi>51.</hi> par. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>459.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> well obſerveth, <hi>the Devill ſeeing his Temples forſaken, and that mankind began to runne after the name of a Redeemer, or delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Mediatour, he ſtirred up heretickes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Chriſtians, to undermine and oppoſe the Doctrine of Chriſt.</hi> For<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mar. 5.17. Luke 10.26. and c. 18.21.18, 19, 20. Mar. 10.19.</note> Chriſt in the Goſpel confirmed the Law, and the hereticks, as the Marcionites and Manichees (beſides others) oppoſed it. Whereupon they are poſed with this queſtion by <hi>Athanaſius</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Athan. diſput. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma contra Arian. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>113.</hi>
                  </note>: <hi>What hath Marcion or Manichaeus to doe with the Goſpel when they abrogate the Law?</hi> And<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Clemens. Alenandr. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. <hi>189.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>a ſort of heretickes called</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tactae <hi>ſo far contemned and affronted it, that becauſe the law ſaid, Thou ſhalt not commit adultery, they profeſſed they would commit adultery.</hi> And this impure purpoſe and practiſe of theirs, they grounded upon an impious principle of their own, holding two Gods, a firſt and a ſecond: the ſecond (they ſaid) ſowed tares, corrupted mankind, and gave the Law, in breaking whereof, they make account they have revenged the wrong of the firſt and better God, upon the ſecond and worſe.</p>
               <p>The ſame Devill which ſuggeſted ſuch wild and wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits to them, hath taught ſome of our times<note n="(e)" place="margin">Teſtim. to the truth, &amp;c. p. 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>to make the Chappel of</hi> Rome <hi>the Church of Chriſt, the brand ſet in the forehead of the great whore, becauſe it is in the Frontiſpice of all the Catholique Confeſſions, as you have noted in your Catalogue.</hi> And the Devills Amanuenſis doubtleſſe he was, who not many yeers ſince wrote the book of Mans Mortality, which preſents to the world a gallipot of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for an Alablaſter-box of Spikenard, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.3. in which peſtilent Pamphlet, are ſuch blaſphemous and abſurd aſſertions, as Religion may abhorre, and reaſon deride; and that ſuch poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonful pills may be ſwallowed with the leſſe ſuſpition of danger; they are ſugared over with prefatory praiſes; and the doctrine of the immortality of the ſoul, that it may be diſtaſted and deteſted,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65388:10"/>blaſphemouſly reproached, as if it had been rather raiſed up out of hell, then ſent downe from heaven.</p>
               <p>And can wee take notice of ſuch notorious and horrid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the truth and honour of our God, and not be ſo far moved with them, as to teſtifie our conſent with our godly bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren againſt them? God forbid, yea we hold it our duties in true zeal to his glory, rather to become emulous of the melting ſpirit of <hi>David,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>rivers of water run downe mine eyes becauſe men keep not thy law, Pſal.</hi> 119.136. how much more, when they doe not only not keepe the law, but teach men to break and to contemne the law, and as much as in them lyeth, to diſanull and deſtroy the law; not only the law of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27. as this impious miſcreant forementioned would doe, but the law of workes alſo (the rule of life, which is another law of the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame place) as the <hi>Antinomians</hi> goe about to doe; both contradicting and blaſpheming them, as the Jews did <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45. and the <hi>Anti-Scripturiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> who doe the like againſt them both, Law and Goſpel, as you have ſhewed in your<note n="(f)" place="margin">Teſtim. to the truth, &amp;c. p. 5. 15, 16.</note> Teſtimony; <hi>It is time for thee O Lord to work, for they have made voide thy Law, Pſal.</hi> 119.126. and for the Lords ſervants to worke with him, and for him, and to contend for the Emphaticall concluſion of the Apoſtle, <hi>Doe we make void the Law through faith? God forbid, yea we eſtabliſh the Law, Rom.</hi> 3.31. And while many are ſo lewdly lawleſſe, as our late errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and hereticall Rabſhakeh's have ſhewed themſelves to be; <hi>We cannot but call</hi> to mind the deep ſenſe that King <hi>Hez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kiah</hi> had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the blaſphemous reproaches of the Aſſyrian Generall, when at the hearing <hi>of them he rent his cloaths, covered himſelfe with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, went into the houſe of the Lord,</hi> and made other patheticall expreſſions, which ſhewed how much he was perplexed for the diſhonour of his God thereby, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.1-4. Nor can wee but deſire and endeavour to be affected (as he was) with due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to the impieties and provocations of our preſent times, and to give ſuch demonſtration thereof as the cauſe requireth, and the opportunity affordeth.</p>
               <p>And though Miniſters be inferiour to Kings in honour, yet in zeal to the glory of God they ſhould not be ſecond to any, how great ſoever, but Fore-men rather as the Levites were, who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65388:10"/>(when God was diſhonoured by that ſtupid Idolatry, in making and worſhipping the golden calfe, and <hi>Moſes</hi> demanded <hi>who is on the Lords ſide, Exod.</hi> 32.26.) came with their ſwords by their ſides and did preſent execution upon the principall tranſgreſſors; and albeit we be no ſuch ſword-men as they were, nor have any thing to doe with bloody ſacrifices as they had, yet we are not without our weapons (which may bee of uſe for conviction, though not as thoſe in their hands, for execution of ſuch as are injurious and blaſphemous againſt the glory of God, as that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry was, and our modern hereſies are) with our tongues and pens we may plead for the propriety and purity of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, againſt all who any way ſeek to oppoſe or eclipſe it. And remembring how great the zeale of <hi>Moſes</hi> was to the glory of God, when rather then the Heathen ſhould have any occaſion reproachfully to miſreport his judiciall proceedings with his people in the wilderneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.12. he wiſheth that his name might be blotted out of Gods booke, <hi>ver.</hi> 32. We take it to be but a ſlender teſtimony of our zeale to the glory of our Maker and Redeemer to ſubſcribe a printed Teſtimony to the truth of Chriſt Jeſus. Nor ſhould we thinke it too much (if there were cauſe to require ſuch a ſervice at our hands) to ſet forth a<note n="*" place="margin">Betwixt the penning and printing of this Atteſtation, there came forth a briefe yet ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, W. in the name of the Miniſters of <hi>Devon.</hi> Printed by <hi>William Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> for <hi>Ralph. Smith.</hi>
                  </note> juſt volume for vindication of his glory, againſt the hereticall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement of this wicked and wretched age wherein we live.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>As we are called Divines and under that Title and in relation to our great and gratious Lord (whoſe Ambaſſadors wee are, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.) we ſtand obliged to be affectionately ſenſible of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing wherein his honour is concerned; So in our relation from him to the people as <hi>watch-men over their ſoules, Heb.</hi> 13.17. we may take a ſecond reaſon from the tender care we ought to have of their eternall welfare, which muſt needs be deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered by ſuch erroneous, hereticall and blaſphemous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as have been too boldly divulged, and but too tamely tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our dayes.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle and Diſciple whom our Saviour eſpecially loved, profeſſed in his epiſtle to <hi>Gaius, that hee had no greater joy then to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65388:11"/>heare that his children walke in truth,</hi> 3. Epiſt. of <hi>John</hi> v. 4. It muſt needs then be one of his greateſt griefs to heare that they wandred and went aſide out of truths high-way, to by-paths of errors and hereſies. For the word of hereticall ſeducers fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth or eateth into the ſoul as a canker, or (as the originall hath hath it) a Gangrene, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17. doth the body. Which<note n="(g)" place="margin">Nominant Gangranas eas, quae ex mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudi ne inflammationis fiunt mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, quae nondum integrae factae ſunt: nam cum omnino membrum affectum eſt emortuum, ut punctum vel ſectum vel aduſtum non ſentiat quae patitur; ſtatim recidere opor tet quae ſanam partem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinam attingunt. Gal. de art. Curat. Tom. <hi>6.</hi> operum. col. <hi>403.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Galen</hi> treateth of as two diſtinct evills. And of the Gangrene he ſaith, <hi>it kills where it infects, making the fleſh dead that is infected by it, ſo that whether prickt or cut or burned, it is unſenſible of any paine. Yet proceeding with ſo much perill from one part to another, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the part corrupted be cut off, it will goe on to bring the whole into the like deſperate and deadly condition.</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Depravant quae ſunt Dei &amp; adulterant verbum Dei, lacte gypſum male miſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Iteneus. adv. haereſ. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> p. <hi>281.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> compareth the doctrine of heretickes to milke mingled with lime or plaſter, and that ſuch a potion is poyſon<note n="(i)" place="margin">Exemplum illuſtre C. Proculeium —in maximo ſtomachi dolore gypſo conſciviſſe ſibi mortem. Plin. Nat. Hiſt. l. <hi>36.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> p. <hi>512.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pliny ſheweth by experience</hi> upon <hi>C. Proculei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> a familiar friend of <hi>Auguſtus Ceſars,</hi> who making triall of it upon him, got his death by it. In reſpect of both theſe bad effects, the one without, the other within, both of them deadly and deſtructive to the ſouls of men; the accuſation of<note n="(k)" place="margin">Vir Sanguinum omnis haereticus, qui quotidie animarum ſanguiném fundit. Hieron. in Pſal. <hi>5.</hi> Tom. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> may be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified againſt an heretick; which is, <hi>that hee is a man of blood,</hi> who dayly is guilty of the blood of ſoules; and ſo ſhould we be, if we ſhould be ſilent when we have a ſtrict charge to watch over them, to forewarne them of their danger, that they may take heed of it; and we conceive this way of warning may be very uſefull, as a common ſhout of the Shepheards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, againſt the Wolfe in Sheeps clothing, though a <hi>Lion feare it not, Iſay</hi> 31.4.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, A third reaſon which engageth us to a publick at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of thoſe truths whereunto you have given teſtimony, and the diſclaiming of errours as you have done, is the reſpect which of duty we ought to bear to the publick welfare of the Kingdome; both in point of ſafety and of honour. Firſt, for ſafetie, and that from a double danger, the one of corruption of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65388:11"/>faith, ſociety, and civill juſtice;<note n="(l)" place="margin">Haud ſcio an pietate adverſus deos ſublata, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des etiam &amp; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietas humani generis, &amp; una excellentiſſima juſtitia virtus tollatur. Cicer. Tuſc. quaeſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>197.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for if piety towards God be takere away,</hi> (and with toleration of all opinions in Religion, it cannot conſiſt) <hi>as the Roman Oratour inferreth, faith and that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent virtue Iuſtice which upholds humane ſociety, will fail,</hi> for the adminiſtration whereof, the deciſion of differences, and the ſtinting of ſtrife is reſolved in the Teſtimony of an oath; as the Apoſtle ſheweth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. And what aſſurance of an oath, if it be not rooted in Religion, &amp; how unſtable will that root be with many, when they are ſubject to be ſhaken with multiplicity of windes of erroneous doctrine? <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. The other danger is of the ruine of the weal publick, which is haſtened &amp; ſometimes ſuddainly brought on (to the deſtruction of Cities) by evill ſtudies, and evill doctrines;<note n="(m)" place="margin">Vetus Graecia longe providens quam ſenſim pernicies illap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa civium animos malis ſtudiis, maliſque doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, repenie totas civitates everte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Cicer l. <hi>2.</hi> de legibus p. <hi>330.</hi> med.</note> 
                  <hi>Heathen yet very prudent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts have obſerved,</hi> although perhaps they were not ſo wiſe as to know the radicall or originall cauſe thereof, which is the juſt judgement of God, for the wickedneſſe of men in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, for their licentiouſneſſe in fond and falſe opinions, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious practices. And <hi>for the honour of our Church and State,</hi> how much is it impeached both at home and abroad, by the infamy of ſo many errors, hereſies, and Sects as have been, and yet are, too much tolerated among us? What a ſhame and reproach is it to our nation at this day to ſee it in print from beyond ſea, and that not by a Papiſt, but<note n="(n)" place="margin">Anglia his <hi>4.</hi> annis facta eſt colluvies &amp; Lerna omnium errorum &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarum: nulla a condito orbe, Provincia tam pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vo ſpatio tot monſtroſas haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes protulit. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que haec Honorus Reggus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar. de ſtatie Eccleſ. in Anglia p. <hi>1.</hi> praefat.</note> a Proteſtant Divine, <hi>That</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>within this four yeers is become the ſinke and lake of</hi> Hydra <hi>for all errors and ſects, no Province from the beginning of the world, in ſo ſhort a ſpace, hath brought forth ſo many, ſo monſtrous hereſies, as</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>hath done.</hi> Againſt theſe two great evills both of danger and diſgrace, the beſt remedy and apologie we can hope for is this, that publick perſons doe openly profeſſe againſt errors and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies. The Parliament hath done it thrice in moſt publick man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, once in their firſt Declaration, <hi>where they ſay</hi> (and a worthy<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> Ep. ded. before his treatiſe of Divin: p. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Member of the Honorable Houſe of Commons</hi> remembers them of it, in an epiſtle dedicatory to them,) <hi>It is far from our purpoſe to deſire to let looſe the golden reynes of diſcipline and government in the Church, to leave private perſons, or particular congregations, to take up what forme of Divine ſervice they pleaſe; for we hold it requiſite, that there ſhould he throughout the whole Realm a conformitie to that Order, which the lawes enjoyne, according to the word of God.</hi> Secondly, in their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65388:12"/>Ordinance of the 4. of <hi>February,</hi> 1646. for a day of humiliation of the whole Kingdome in regard of the growth of thoſe wicked windes of errour, &amp;c. <hi>Which</hi> being worthy of perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, that it may not bee loſt in a looſe ſheet, (for the glory of God, and honour of the Parliament) we conceive it convenient wholly to inſert in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="ordinance">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Die Iovis</hi> 4. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1646.</date> An Ordinance of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aſſembled in Parliament, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the growth and ſpreading of Errors, Hereſies, and Blaſphemies; ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart a day of publique humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation to ſeek Gods aſſiſtance, for the ſuppreſſing and preventing the ſame.</opener>
                        <p>VVEE the Lords and Commons Aſsembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> having entered into a Solemn League and Covenant, to indeavour ſincerely, really, and conſtantly, the Reformation of Religion, in Doctrine, Diſcipline and Worſhip: and the extirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Popery, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall bee found contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of godlineſse; and having found the preſence of God wonderfully aſsiſting us in this cauſe, eſpecially ſince our ſaid engagement in purſuance of the ſaid Covenant: Have thought fit (leſt wee partake in other mens ſinnes, and thereby bee in danger to receive of their plagues) to ſet forth this our deepe ſenſe of the great diſhonour of God, and perilous condition that this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65388:12"/>is in, through the abominable blaſphemies, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hereſies vented and ſpread abroad therein, tending to the ſubverſion of the faith, contempt of the Miniſtery, and Ordinance of Ieſus Chriſt: And as wee are reſolved to imploy and improve the utmost of our power, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be ſaid or done againſt the truth, but for the truth, ſo wee deſire that both our ſelves and the whole Kingdome may bee deeply humbled before the Lord for that great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and contempt, which hath beene caſt upon his name and ſaving truths, and for that ſwift deſtruction, which wee may juſtly feare will fall upon the immortall ſoules of ſuch who are or may bee drawne away, by giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits. In the hearty and tender compaſsion whereof wee the ſaid Lords and Commons Order and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, that Wedneſday being the <hi>10.</hi> day of <hi>March</hi> next, be ſet apart for a day of publique Humiliation, for the growth &amp; ſpreading of erros, hereſies &amp; blaſphemies, to be obſerved in all places within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> and to ſeek God for his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and aſsiſtance, for the ſuppreſſing and preventing of the ſame; and all Miniſters are hereby injoyned to publiſh this preſent Ordinance upon the Lords Day, preceding the ſaid tenth day of <hi>March.</hi> Ordered to bee printed, and copies to be ſent abroad by the Members that ſerve for the reſpective Counties, Cities, and Burroughs.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, by their Ordinance of the 2. of <hi>May,</hi> forementioned for the puniſhing of Blaſphemies and hereſies, which wee preſume had been ſooner ſet forth, if the diſtempers of the times had not defrauded them of fit opportunities for ſuch a publication, and the Miniſters doing their parts to the ſame purpoſe to cry down errours, &amp;c. by preaching and writing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65388:13"/>them, there is the leſſe cauſe to feare a publique guilt and perill of the Kingdome, and a fairer defence againſt the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of reproach, though they bee not ſo farre ſuppreſſed as they ſhould bee.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, A fourth reaſon why wee thus publiquely profeſſe againſt errors &amp;c. with you is, becauſe of the <hi>ſubtilty, ſedulity</hi> and <hi>pride</hi> of hereticks; 1. For their ſubtilty, they are as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Elymas, full of all ſubtilty</hi> (though but the children of the devill) as hee calls him <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10. for the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Hoſt is noſter cui mille nocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di artes. Epiſt. Paulim &amp; The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiae Auguſt in. Aug. <hi>31.</hi> p. <hi>133.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Devill their father, who hath a thouſand deceiptfull arts or devices to doe hurt,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth them in pernicious fallacies, and teacheth them to make choice of ſuch perſons to worke upon as are moſt eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and ſuch wayes to worke by, as may bee moſt probable for prevailing: Upon this ground doth <hi>Gregory Nazianzen poſe</hi> an Impoſtor in his time<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gr. Naz. orat. <hi>33.</hi> Tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>535.</hi>
                  </note>, <hi>Why</hi> ſaith hee <hi>doſt thou gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the filth of a ſinke into one gulfe every vaine and light witted man, not worthy indeed of the name of men, and by ſubtilty of ſpeech, having made them more and more effeminate, haſt ſet up a new ſhoppe of impiety, and by abuſing their madneſſe, haſt craftily contrived an harveſt of advantage to thy ſelfe?</hi> 2. For ſedulity, as the Devill is a perpetuall Peripatetick continually going <hi>to</hi> and <hi>fro in the earth, and walking up and downe in it, Iob</hi> 1.7, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. So his agents and emiſſaries hereticall teachers (as our Saviour ſaid of the Scribes and Phariſees) compaſſe Sea and land, to make a proſelyte, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.15. Thus doe the Jeſuites at this day,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Philip. Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gambe Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theca, Scriptor. Societ. Ieſu. paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim.</note> as <hi>one of their own Order ſheweth by manifold examples:</hi> and both they and other ſeducers came of late from forain parts to ſow their tares of errours in our fields. 3. For pride, they are many of them of the high mind of <hi>Eunomius</hi> the heretick, whom it would not ſuffice, (as <hi>the ſame ancient Orthodox</hi>
                  <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Greg. Naz. orat. <hi>46.</hi> p. <hi>721.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Doctor obſerveth of him</hi>) <hi>to bee of ſome account, and to have a number of Diſciples, but hee tooke it for a detriment to himſelf, unleſſe he might draw all to deſtruction, after him.</hi> The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof may give us juſt cauſe to caſt about<note n="(t)" place="margin">Hoſtis noſter tam variis expug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandus eſt telis quam oppugnat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidiis. Ep. Paulini &amp; Theraſ. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino. Aug. Ep. <hi>31.</hi> p. <hi>133.</hi>
                  </note> to <hi>overcome them as many wayes, as they come to aſſault or oppoſe the truth:</hi> and we conceive this way of unanimous diſcovery and deteſtation of errours, &amp;c. to be of great moment, to that purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65388:13"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>FIthly, A fifth reaſon, why wee thinke it requiſite thus to expreſſe our ſelves opponents to errors, &amp;c. is, becauſe of the common people, who by <hi>their levity and inclination toward vagrant ſpeculations,</hi> as<note n="(v)" place="margin">Tanta plereſque titillat vagtrum ſpeculatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cupido; tantaque levitas circumagit, ut facile ſit impoſtoribus, quemvis nec ingenio nec, &amp;c. Calvin expl. perfldiae Valinten. Gentil opuſc. p. <hi>672.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> calls them, are apt to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by ſuch impoſters as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, or wit, or learning, or dexterity draw ſuch diſciples after them; and as they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to bee deceived, ſoare they wilfull when they are deceived.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, the obſervation of<note n="(w)" place="margin">Nihil tam facile eſt, quam vilem plebeculam linguae volubilitate decipere, quae quicquid non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligit, plus miratur. Hieron. ad Nepotianum de vita Clericorum. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>70.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> hath beene verified in divers ages (ours for one,) <hi>that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo eaſie as to deceive the vile vulgar ſort, with a voluble tongue, who admire every thing ſo much the more as they leſſe underſtand it;</hi> and it may be their Teachers doe not underſtand themſelves, for<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s imperitorum Magiſtri quam doctorum diſcipuli. Hieron. ad Demitr. Tom p. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> ſome <hi>of them,</hi> as hee ſaith, <hi>are Masters of the ignorant, before they have beene ſcholars of the Learned.</hi> And they are not more ignorant then confident, and obſtinate too, as the<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ad quamvis diſciplinam quaſi tempeſtate delati ad eam tanquam ad Saxum adhaereſcunt. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Acad. qu. lib. <hi>2.</hi> p <hi>4.</hi> fin.</note> 
                  <hi>Oratour obſerveth, to what diſcipline ſoever they are carryed as with a tempeſt, to that as to a rock they ſtick, and they</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">Veſtra ſolum legitis, veſtra amatis, caeteros cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa incognita condemnatis, Cicir. de nat. Deor. l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>226.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>read onely what is written on their own ſide, not vouchſafing a view of any thing againſt it, and ſo condemning the innocent without taking cognizance of their cauſe.</hi> That's the manner of many ſeduced Diſciples amongſt us, who are well acquainted with ſhort ſeducing Pamphlets, but will neither bee at coſt nor paines to read full and ſolid diſcourſes made in confutation of them, and many times they are, or pretend themſelves ignorant, that any ſuch are extant, as if they had<note n="(a)" place="margin">Errare ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo cum Platone quam cum iſtis vera ſentire. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Tuſc. quaeſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>122.</hi>
                  </note> reſolved <hi>rather to erre with ſome, then to think right with others.</hi> Of this pertinacious perſiſting in error, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> rendereth a double reaſon, or cauſe rather, (for reaſon it hath none) <hi>every one is a ſhamed</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eruleſcit quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vàm mutare ſententiam, ne aut inconſtans putetur, aut diu erraſſe ſe ipſo judice te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaur. Aug. ad Deogratias Epiſt. <hi>48.</hi> p. <hi>214.</hi>
                  </note> (ſaith he) <hi>to part with an evill opinion, leſt hee ſhould be thought unconſtant,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65388:14"/>or be made, by his amendment, a condemning Judge againſt himſelf for having continued ſo long in his precedent errour:</hi> though of ſome wee may ſay, that they are very fickle as well as very falſe in their opinions, affecting as<note n="(c)" place="margin">Affectant per ſingulos dies, novum aliquod adinvenire, &amp; fructificare quod nunquam quiſquam excogitavit. Irenaeus adv. Haereſ. p. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi> p. <hi>111.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> noteth, <hi>to find out ſome new thing every day, to bring forth ſomewhat that hath not beene thought of by any one before them;</hi> in regard hereof, though ſome may bee ſo farre gone, in erroneous and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious folly and frenzy; that <hi>as</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſae terrae Elleborum non ſufficit ad expurgandum, ut evomant tantam ſtultitiam. Iren. ibid. cap. <hi>53.</hi> p. <hi>210.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus ſaith, all the ellebore in the earth</hi> (<hi>a</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Elleborum medetur vertigini, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicis, inſanientibus, lymphaticis, Plin. Nat. Hiſt. l. <hi>25.</hi> ca. <hi>5.367.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſoveraign antidote againſt brainſicke diſtempers</hi>) <hi>will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them to their right mindes.</hi> Yet ſince (as<note n="(f)" place="margin">Primus ſapientiae gradus eſt falſa intelligere. Lact. Juſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi> p. <hi>104.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> noteth) <hi>the firſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gree of wiſdome is to know what is falſe,</hi> thoſe that are not at all, or not deeply tainted with any of them, may become wiſer by your Catalogue of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, &amp;c. And by the common conſent of Miniſters conteſting againſt them, may be more confirmed in the Orthodox Faith.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Wee take the zeale of the antient Fathers for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable inducement, for us thus to appeare in oppoſition to errours, &amp;c. as of the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Bin. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Conc p. <hi>322.</hi>
                  </note> 318. Fathers aſſembled, <hi>Anno</hi> 325. in the firſt councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> eſpecially for the ſuppreſſion of the <hi>Arian</hi> hereſie, where<note n="(i)" place="margin">Epiph. Haere. <hi>69.</hi> Aug. Haereſ. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Arius</hi> was condemned by a common Vote, and ſo were other hereticks in other councels. But we conſider not onely their number, and conſent as a motive unto us, for what wee now preſent to your view, but take it, for an incentive for more ſervour in our Deteſtation of hereſies, that ſome of them have opened their mouths in ſevere cenſures, and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reprehenſions of them, as <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpus</hi> (who lived in the time of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Evang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> liſt</hi>) and outlived him, though he dyed a Martyr.<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <p>Polycarpus Marcioni aliquando occurrenti &amp; ſibi dicenti, Cognoſce nos, reſpondit, Cognoſco te eſſe primogeniuim Satanae. Irenae. <hi>9.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> adv. haereſ. cap. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>233.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Simile etiam de Polycarpo referiur ad Florinum ex Euſebio l. <hi>5.</hi> c <hi>19.</hi> addit. oper. Irena. p. <hi>510.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> When <hi>Marcion the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticke would have him take knowledge of him, I know thee (ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e) to bee the firſt berne of Satan.</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Quibus. (i.e. ſanctis patribus) ſi aliquis annunciavetit ea quae ab haeratiois ad inventa ſunt—ſtatim concludentes aures. longe longius fugerent, ne audire ſuſtinentes blaſphem. colloqu. Irenae. adv. Haereſ. l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>242.</hi>
                  </note> Some of them have ſtopped their eares at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65388:14"/>of hereticall inventions.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Claudite aures qui auditu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri eſtis, ne impietatis vocibus polluamini. Hieron. adverſ. Lucifer. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>143.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> being to repeate a hereticall baptiſme, <hi>bade his auditory ſtop their eares, leſt by hearing it, they ſhould bee polluted with impiety.</hi> By which Preface hee prepared their hearts to an hatred of it, and then though they heard it, they were the leſſe in danger to bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by it. And for this Author he was ſo ſarre both from partiall and timorous ſilence towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom hee held for an heretick, that when hee was moved to moderation to ſuch kind of men, his anſwer was this,<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>no tibi conſentire non poſſum, ut parcam haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis me catholicum non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent; ſi iſta cauſa diſcordiae, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri poſſum, tacere non poſſum; Hieron. Apol. adv. Ruff. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>244.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In one thing I cannot conſent unto thee, that by ſparing of heretickes I ſhould not ſhew my ſelfe to be a Catholique, if that be a cauſe of diſcord, dye I can, but hold my peace againſt ſuch perſons I cannot.</hi> And if he were ſometimes too rough and ruffled too much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as were oppoſite to him in opinion (though on this ſide hereſie) as indeed hee did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Vigilantius</hi> (for which he is juſtly taken up by<note n="(o)" place="margin">In hunc, id eſt, Vigilanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ita debacchatur Hierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ut pluſculum in eo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiae cogar deſiderare. utinam argumentis duntaxd tegiſſet, &amp; a convitiis temperaſſet. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſm. Argument. in Hiero. Ep. adv. Vigil. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eraſmus:</hi>) yet both he and the moſt of the ancient Fathers of beſt account, as <hi>Irenaeus, Cyprian, Epiphanius, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> were ſuch zealots againſt errours, eſpecially hereticall and blaſphemous opinions, that having ſo great a cauſe and ſo faire an occaſion to declare our diſlike of them (as you have done.) wee might bee judged degenerated ſonnes of ſuch Reverend Fathers, if wee ſhould not joyne with our venerable, Brethren as now wee doe, in a Proteſtation againſt them.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Wee tooke into our thoughts the Synod at <hi>Dort,</hi> againſt the Arminians, and the Atteſtations of other<note n="p" place="margin">As of <hi>Peter Du. Moulin</hi> and others, who gave their aſſent in writing to the Synod, though they were not at it.</note> Divines thereto, (who were not called to it, or not permitted to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it,) as an imitable example for conſentient teſtimonie of Miniſters againſt errors, &amp;c. It will not, we hope, ſeeme an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, in this place (ſince the cauſe is the ſame, though the perſons bee of a farr higher ranke) to rehearſe the Declaration of King <hi>James</hi> in his proſecution of a complaint to the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> againſt <hi>Conradus Vorſtius</hi> a <hi>wretched hereticke,</hi> or rather <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> (as hee calleth him) whom hee would not indure to bee harboured in a neighbour Country, much leſſe in any of his own Dominions. For thus may ſuch an inſtance reaſonably induce us to a publique profeſſion againſt errours, &amp;c. and the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65388:15"/>toleration of them: if a King were ſo zealous againſt the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of one particular man infected with unſound princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and at ſuch a diſtance from danger to his owne people (though hee might bee the more zealous as hee was intitled, Defender of the Faith),<note n="(r)" place="margin">Henry the 8. had that ſent him by the Pope for wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting for Popery againſt Mr. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fox. Mart. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>c.</hi> 2 <hi>nu</hi> 20. <hi>Speeds Chron. in</hi> H. 8. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.1. <hi>par.</hi> 38, 39. <hi>p.</hi> 1007.</note> 
                  <hi>a contrary faith</hi> to that which in that ſtile was firſt intended; Should not Gods Miniſters be awakened and quickned zealouſly to conteſt againſt Domeſtick Seducers, by whom their flockes may bee in danger to be deſtroyed?</p>
               <p>Eightly, If we ſhould not be very apprehenſive of the prejudice and reproach of Divine truths, and Doctrines of Piety by the multiplicity of erroneous opinions, hereſies, blaſphemies, and perjuries in the breach of Covenant, and the toleration of them; Wee will not ſay (as ſome have hyperbolically ſpoken of the ſupply of their own ſilence,<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Iohn Goodwin, Sion</hi> Colledge viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, page 26.</note> 
                  <hi>That the ſtones of the streets and tiles of the houſes would cry, ſhould they hold their peace,</hi> but we conceive that heathens might riſe up in judgement againſt us and condemne us, for if wee ſhould bee mute (while hereſie is ſo loud) they would bee found more faithfull to a falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then wee to a true. What the morall ſort of ſuch men have both ſaid and done for their Religion (as for the Greeks, <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Plutarch,</hi> for the Latines, <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi>) would make up a copious accuſation of our Laodicean Neutrall or meere nominall Chriſtians of this age; Wee may have enough to our purpoſe out of one of them, even <hi>Cicero,</hi> whom becauſe hee was both a prudent Moraliſt and an eloquent Orator, and well read in the beſt Authors of both Languges, we may preſent as Speaker for the reſt; and of him we may learne to take heed how wee make light of any peece or particle of Religion, where<note n="(t)" place="margin">Aut undiqua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Religionem tolle, aut uſquequaque conſerva. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cer. Phil. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>239.</hi> h. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> hee ſaith, that <hi>Religion is no better then alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether abandoned, if it bee not every way and intirely maintained:</hi> and for making conſcience of an oath or Covenant, wee may obſerve much of his well meaning this way by his definition of an Oath, and the obligation upon it,<note n="(v)" place="margin">Ius jurandum eſt affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Religi ſa Deo teſtie. Cicer. de offic p. <hi>404.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>an Oath</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a religious affirmation,</hi> and of what a man ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth God is witneſſe, <hi>and with God his own mind,</hi> (that is, <hi>his conſcience,</hi>)<note n="(w)" place="margin">Cum jurato dicenda ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia meminer it ſe adhibere te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent mentein ſuam, qua nibil ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni dedit ipſe deus divinius. Cicer. de offic. l. <hi>3.</hi> p <hi>395.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>then which God hath given nothing unto man more Divine, and</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Quod affirmate Deo teſte promiſeris tenendum. ibid. p. <hi>404.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>what is ſo witneſſed, affirmed, or promiſed, muſt be kept,</hi> though to a mans loſſe, yea though to the loſſe of a mans
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65388:15"/>life, and hee commendeth the couragious and conſcientious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of <hi>Regulus,</hi> who taken Captive in the firſt Punick Warre was ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi> for an exchange of priſoners, which if hee did not effect, he was upon oath by his return to render himſelfe into the hands of his enemies, <hi>and</hi>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">Captivos reddendes in ſenatu non cenſuit; deinde cum retineretur ab amicis, ad ſupplicium redire maluit quam fidem hoſti datam fallere. Ibi. lib. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>356.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>when hee had given his opinion, that it was not expedient for his Country men to give back their cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, for his oathes ſake, and againſt the diſſwaſion of his friends he came back to ſuffer puniſhment by his enemies rather then hee would ſalſifie the faith he had given to them.</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">Cum vigilando necabatur, erat in meliore cauſa, quam ſi domi ſenex captivus perjurus &amp; conſularis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſiſſet. ibid. l. <hi>3</hi> p. <hi>404.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And though he were killed hee was in a better condition (ſaith Cicero) then if hee had ſtayed an old perjured, and conſular Captive in his own count ey.</hi> And that wee may know that heathen Romans are more to bee truſted (as more true of their words) then Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Romaniſts at this day, hee condemnes their tenet who hold that faith <hi>with an infidell</hi> (or as they ſay, with an heretick) is <hi>not to bee kept;</hi> and hee bids them that are of that opinion take heed<note n="(a)" place="margin">Si ſibi ſumunt nullam eſſe fidem quae infideli data ſit, videant ne quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur latebra perjurio. Cicer. de offic. l. <hi>3.</hi> p <hi>404.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that they make it not a lurking place for perjury,</hi> whereof a man ſhould not bee guilty though it were to advance the welfare of the Common weale: for he holds there be degrees of the duty of man, the firſt to God, the ſecond to his Country, and the third to his parents, and then to others according to their rankes, ſo that Religion muſt have the firſt place, and by Religion, (eſpecially by religious taking and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of oathes and Covenants) humane ſocieties are ſecured and preſerved.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Quam multa firmantur jurejurando? quantae ſalutis ſunt faedera Religionis? quam multos Divini ſupplicii meius a ſcelere revocavit? quainque Sancta ſocietas civium inter ipſos, diis immortalibus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitis tum Judicibus tum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus? Cicer. de legib. l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>326.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>How many things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are confirmed by an Oath? of how great ſafety are confederacies of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? how many hath the fear of Divine vengeance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held from Villany? how holy is the ſociety of Citizens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, God being interpoſed both as a Judge and as a witneſſe betwixt them?</hi> Upon this ground, minding to gaine extraordinary credit and confidence, to an Epiſtle which hee wrote to <hi>Licinius</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Has literas velim exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes faederis habituras eſſe vim non Epiſtolae, me<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ea quae tibi. promitio ac recipio ſanctiſſime eſſe obſervaturum. Cicer. Ep, ad Licin. l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>he deſired him to beleeve there was the force of a Covenant in it, not of an Epiſtle, wherein what hee promiſed, he meant moſt holily to performe.</hi> And touching Toleration of impious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, we may know what his mind was, by that hee reporteth and approveth of <hi>Protagoras</hi> Bookes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65388:16"/>being burned, and himſelfe (for ſpeaking doubtfully of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) baniſhed,<note place="margin">Cicer. de nat. deor. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>206</hi>
                  </note> and this by the ſentence of the Judges of <hi>Athens,</hi> ſo that we may ſee the zeal of the moſt eminent, both <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romanes</hi> in this example, who though they were Barbarians to one another (eſpecially the <hi>Romanes</hi> to the <hi>Greekes, Rom.</hi> 14.15.) wee that are Chriſtians ſhould bee more unworthy and much worſe then either (our greater light adding much to the aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our guilt) if wee ſhould not deeply take to heart the diſhonour of God by errours, &amp;c. and the toleration of them, and willingly put to our hands with our Reverend and godly Brethren, in a Teſtimony to the truth of Jeſus Chriſt, and to our Solemn League and Covenant made againſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>Ninethly, Wee conceive it the more requiſite thus to appear in profeſſion of the ſame truths and oppoſition of the ſame er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, &amp;c. with you, leſt we ſhould incurre a <hi>double danger,</hi> the <hi>one of ſinne,</hi> the other of <hi>puniſhment; the ſinne,</hi> wee would bee loath ſhould bee charged upon us, is a treacherous or timorous ſilence, (like that condemned by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> in his time, chap. 9. verſe 3.) when there is juſt occaſion or rather urgent neceſſity to declare our minds in the cauſe of our Saviour Chriſt, as you have done. The <hi>puniſhment</hi> wee have cauſe to feare (if we ſhould be afraid thus to diſcover the dictates of our conſciences) is <hi>twofold,</hi> the one <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> the other <hi>temporall,</hi> the former no leſſe then the great curſe of <hi>Anathems Maranatha</hi> for lacke of love to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. for what love beare wee to him, if wee forbeare to witneſſe a good confeſſion for him or his truth, when ſo many falſe witneſſes are riſen up againſt them both? and for <hi>temporall puniſhments,</hi> wee may according to the obſervation of<note n="(d)" place="margin">Plerun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ab a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li is docendis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando etiam objurgandis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le diſſimulatur, quia peccatis eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundem damnab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus parcunt, jure cum iis, temporaliter fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellantur, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis in aeternum minime puniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Aug. de Civ. Dei l. c. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine, juſtly expect a ſhare in them, with thoſe whoſe great provocations of Gods wrath, doe moſt procure them by a ſilent conſent or connivence towards the wickedneſſe of the times wherein wee live,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Vel cum labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris piget, vel os eorum verecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damur offendere, vel cum eorum inimicitias de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitemus, ne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediant &amp; noce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>whether it proceed of negligence, or baſhfulneſſe, or feare leſt their enmity (whom by diſcharge of our duty we may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend) ſhould either hinder our good or doe us hurt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There may bee another cauſe of a worſe kind then any of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> a Politicke neutrality, when men ſuſpend all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of engagement on either ſide in any publicke breach or
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65388:16"/>diviſion, and reſolve to bee meere ſpectators of a quarrell untill they ſee which way the ſucceſs is like to be ſwayed, that they may make advantagious conditions for themſelves, with the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party. Which <hi>the wiſe</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Solon. apud. Plutarch. in vita Solonis, p. <hi>91. 92.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Governour and Law-maker</hi> of the Greeks (though having no more in him then heathen morality) ſo farre deteſted, that hee branded them with a note of infamie, who <hi>in civile diſcord and ſedition ſate ſtill, and did not joyne with thoſe, that tooke the juſteſt cauſe, and hazard themſelves with ſuch, rather then looking on, (without putting themſelves in danger) to ſee which of the contenders ſhould have the Victory;</hi> Which whether cowardly or cunning refervation and ſuſpence, wee take to bee deeply condemned in our Solemne League and Covenant, under the tearmes of <hi>Deteſtable indifferencie or neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity:</hi> and ſhould wee bee guilty of the breach of it, by keeping ſilence when juſt occaſion and convenient feaſon invites us to an open profeſſion of the truth of Jeſus Chriſt againſt errours, &amp;c. the ſinne of <hi>Tyrus</hi> would make us liable to the Judgment of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> for not remembring, or not regarding the <hi>brotherly Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Amos</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, and laſtly, as we conceive it very reaſonable in reſpect of what wee have already pleaded for publication of this our profeſſion of the ſame minde and meaning with you concerning errours, &amp;c. So wee hope it is very ſeaſonable at this time to doe it ſince wee perceive by the<note n="g" place="margin">Publiſhed <hi>Apr.</hi> 28. 1648. But it came not to our hands, untill the latter end of <hi>May.</hi>
                  </note> humble reprefentation of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, to the honourable Eſtates of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they make our taking of the Covenant and giving Teſtimony againſt the errours, &amp;c. a weighty argument againſt the waging of a new Warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Kingdome and ours, their words are theſe,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Wee are not convinced of any juſt ground for a new Warre againſt that Kingdome in that which hath beene inſtanced by your Lordſhips,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>78.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>eſpecially for that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was taken by the repreſentatives, and other chief Corporations in</hi> England, <hi>whereupon the Generall Aſsem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and Parliament of this Kingdome have frequently mentioned in their Acts, Letters, and Declarations, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65388:17"/>Vnion and Conjunction of both Kingdomes, by Solemne League and Covenant, neither are wee without hopes (if things bee carried on in a faire and right way) that the Kingdome of</hi> England <hi>may be brought to a further length in the performance of this duty. Whereof wee are the more confident, becauſe of the famous and frequent Teſtimonies given to the Covenant, and againſt errors, &amp;c. by the Miniſtery in divers Provinces in</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Which witneſſeth their wonted prudence and piety by ſome of us obſerved in their Honorable and Reverend Commiſſioners ſent unto this Kingdome, for the preventing of a breach among Covenanted Brethren.</p>
               <p>And as our Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> are not convinced of any juſt ground for a new Warre by their Arguments who would raiſe it in their Kingdome againſt ours, ſo wee for the ſame reaſons (with ſome additionalls of moment advancing to an higher degree of evidence and aſſurance,<note n="(h)" place="margin">For it bate date the 28. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> and the penall Ordin. againſt Hereſ. paſſed the 2. of <hi>May.</hi>
                  </note> ſince their humble Repreſentation was printed) are convinced, that there is no juſt warrant for ſuch a Warre as the enemies of our peace and ſafety would enkindle among us, under the oppofite Titles of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For, for the moſt and weightieſt differences betwixt them, wee conceive a Parliament of Legiſlative Senators and an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines are fitter to decide them then two oppoſite Armies: for the reſt we had rather be reſolved then determined by the Long Robe then by the Buffe Coate, by the Judges of the Law, in a diliberate way of inquiry and tryall, then by<note n="(i)" place="margin">Inter arma ſilent leges.</note> lawleſſe ſwordmen in a way of ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie hoſtility and violence, which will allow of no leaſure for <hi>diſtinction</hi> of cauſes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor for <hi>conviction</hi> of errours or offences before <hi>execution.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>ANd though the breach of Covenant bee pretended as a juſt provocation for unſheathing the Sword in a ſecond war
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65388:17"/>(and God we confeſſe may as hee threatneth, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.25. ſend a Sword to avenge the quarrell of his Covenant) yet (as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Commiſſioners well obſerved) the Covenant is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ratified and confirmed then violated by the Repreſentatives and Miniſters of the Counties, or Provinces (as they ſpeake) whoſe owning and avowing of it, is more conſiderable for keeping of peace betwixt the two Kingdomes then the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or contempt of it by others, for breaking out into a new Warre.</p>
               <p>And wee are aſſured that ſuch a Warre as ſome would ſtirr up and carry on under pretence of aſſerting the Covenant againſt Independent Sectaries and Hereticks, would make the breaches of the Covenant wider both in the <hi>Doctrinall</hi> and <hi>Practicall</hi> part thereof.</p>
               <p>For, firſt, for the <hi>Doctrinall part,</hi> though many errours were brewed in the Biſhops times (by occaſion of their tyranizing rule over the conſciences of Chriſtians which made them ſneake into corners, where ordinarily the truth dwelleth not) yet thoſe and many others have beene more boldly broached and more generally propagated by the progreſſe of Warre, and under the protection of the Sword they who hold and publiſh them, make account they may bee more ſecure from cenſure and reſtraint, then in times of peace they can expect to bee.</p>
               <p>And for the <hi>practicall part</hi> (which is too much ſlighted by moſt, while the other is in a manner onely infiſted on) as <hi>that it is our true and unfaigned purpoſe, deſire and endeavour for our ſelves and all others under our power, both in publique and private in all dutie wee ow to God and man, to mend our lives, and to goe before one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the example of a reall Reformation, that the Lord may turn away his wrath and heavy indignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Kingdomes in truth and peace.</hi> Can this bee expected by the Warre now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected? can wee hope for any helpe towards the reſtraint of prophaneneſſe, and promotion of the power of godlineſſe, by ſuch an art as conſiſteth, (as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Praeclara ars incendere domos, diripere Templa, violare virgines, ſpoliare miſeros, occidere innoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os. Eraſm. Collo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Milit. confeſſ. p. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> noteth) <hi>in burning of houſes, battering downe of Churches, violation of Virgins, ſpoiling even of thoſe that are in miſery, killing of the innocent, &amp;c.</hi> May wee not rather feare, that a Civil War of the ſecond Edition, will bee ſet forth like a Maſſe Booke in red and black letters of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65388:18"/>cruelty and uncleanneſs much corrupted &amp; augmented, and that if the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Matt. 12.45.</note> 
                  <hi>evill Spirit caſt out</hi> return upon us, hee will <hi>bring with him ſeven other Spirits more wicked then himſelfe,</hi> and ſo ſhould they prevaile, (which God forbid) our laſt <hi>ſtate would be worſe then the firſt, Matth.</hi> 12.45. Can we look for any better of ſuch as are <hi>impetuouſly ſpurred on,</hi> (as the ſame<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ego nihil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud conjectare poſſum quam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los agi malis furiis, ſeſe<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> totos malo daemoni &amp; miſeriaedevoviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Ibid. p. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> Author ſaith of them) by wicked furies, <hi>as if they had devoted themſelves to devilliſh malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and miſery?</hi> and if ſuch a deſtructive hoſtility ſhould be proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, as ſome purpoſe it, what ever become of the ſectaries and hereticks (moſt ſpoken of) the grand hereticks of the Popiſh faction would bee much incouraged and advanced by it: for if the moſt zealous Antipapiſts ſhould aſſault and ſlay each other, they needed but to bee lookers on untill both ſides being mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually weakned, they might have hope to have both for a prey, and would take it, as if God had ſet us together by the eares to make ſome ſportfull ſpectacle for them to behold, ſo much <hi>Genebrard</hi> meant, when he ſaid,<note n="(n)" place="margin">Deus haerericis haereticos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit ut Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis tacentibus ſe mutuo confici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Genebr. Chronogr. l. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>766.</hi> inter an. <hi>1572-74.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>God ſets hereticks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hereticks, that the Catholiques might bee ſilent ſpectators of their mutuall maſſacres.</hi> Whereby they may expect ſo farre to prevail as to compaſſe their moſt deſtructive deſignes upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant party.</p>
               <p>That moved <hi>Calvin</hi> with paſſionate admiration, to ſay upon the contentions of Evangelicall profeſſors, in his time,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Deus bone! quantos &amp; quam jucundos luſus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus, quaſi illis locave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus operam noſtram. Calv. Ep. Melanthon. p. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Good God! what delight and ſport doe wee make to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts? wee could not gratifie them more then wee doe, by our differences, if they had hired us to doe them ſome acceptable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</hi> For they make account that our conflicts will haſten their conqueſts, and they would bee ſure the more to glory in our ſinnes and ſufferings, becauſe they make<note n="(p)" place="margin">Septima nota eſt, unio membrorum inter ſe &amp; cum capite. Bellarm. de notis. Ecleſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>78.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> unity <hi>their own unity,</hi> a note of the true Church, and<note n="(q)" place="margin">At haeretici diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uni &amp; unus habet alium pro haereitco. Bell. ibid. p. <hi>80.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> diſſention, <hi>our diſſention,</hi> which they obſerve, and aggravate beyond all meaſure, a marke of hereſie. Beſides, there is a prelaticall and otherwiſe Malignant party among us, to whom ſuch as are in <hi>debt, diſtreſſe, and diſcontent,</hi> will bee ready to ſort themſelves, as they did in <hi>Davids</hi> time, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.2. who would make as ill an uſe of our diſcord, (eſpecially if they could heighten it to a warlike hoſtility of the religious of both Nations,) as the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65388:18"/>Papiſts would doe, whereof our<note n="(r)" place="margin">The humble Repreſentation of the Commiſſioners of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly forecited. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> have a jealous apprehenſion, and ſo have wee; and therefore what<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Heu mihi! qui vos ſimul invenire non poſſum, ut moveor, ut doleo! proci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derem ad pedes veſtros, flerem quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vale rem, rogarem quantum ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, nunc utrun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pro ſeipſo, &amp;c. Aug. Hieron. inter opera Hieron. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>355.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine would have done to reconcile</hi> Hierome <hi>and</hi> Ruffinus, <hi>though</hi> but particular Antagoniſts, to take off the diſgrace of their contentions; that and much more, according to the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of ſcandall and of danger would we doe, rather then that any pretended difference betwixt Presbyterians and Independents, or any conſcientious Non-Covenanters ſhould be ſo far exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as to bee put to the blinde and barbarous deciſion of the ſword, wherein they would have moſt to doe, who have leaſt reaſon and Religion, and the moſt of ſuch wild and wicked di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers as are moſt repugnant to them both.</p>
               <p>And for the better part of our diſſenting Brethren at home, we hope they would hold it a matter of duty and of ſafety, (as well as wee doe) to bee at peace with us, and that they will beare with our faithfull dealing in the cauſe of Chriſt; and if in our zeale thereto wee have not ſhewed our ſelves partiall to any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies of opinion or practiſe, we wiſh them to conſider the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note n="(t)" place="margin">Non omnis qui parcit eſſe ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, nec omnis qui verberat, ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> micus, Aug. Vin. Ep. <hi>48.</hi> p. <hi>188.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>every one is not a friend who forbeareth to rebuke, nor every one an enemy who rather ſtriketh then ſtroaketh;</hi> and fince the moſt of them are for a Toleration of different opinions, Worſhips and writings, we cannot but expect their patience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, though thus farre wee have profeſſed againſt them, for even upon their own grounds they muſt allow us the ſame liberty to think, and ſpeak, and write, and act, according to our principles and conſciences, which they aſſume to themſelves and permit unto others; and the rather, becauſe a confiderable ſort and number of them doe not ſo much diſſent from us, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the greateſt moment, as they doe from many of thoſe who under the titles of Independents, (howſoever otherwiſe divided) are united together againſt the Presbyteriall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with reference to ſuch wee further ſay, that (though we approve of the Presbyteriall Government, as moſt conſonant to Scripture, and moſt convenient and commodious, (as a wall of Diſcipline about the Vineyard of Doctrine) for the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65388:19"/>defence of the ſoundneſſe of faith, and holineſſe of life, and therefore could wiſh it were generally received, through the three Kingdomes of the Covenant.) Yet doe wee not deſire the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of it in that extent, to be purchaſed by the price of blood, and therefore we diſavow the diſpute of the ſword, to determine any differences betwixt us. And we hope the godly, both <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> will be ſo wiſe, as to beware of ſuch a breach as may incourage and confirme their enemies, whether Popiſh, Prelaticall, or prophane, againſt them both; whom as<note n="(v)" place="margin">Tu mecum Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorium, me te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum execratur. Neſtor. Arn. &amp; Serap. confl. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. operibus Iren. p. <hi>547.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Arnobius</hi> ſaith to <hi>Serapion, they both alike condemn, and by whom they are both alike abominated,</hi> though for diviſive and deſtructive ends, they may court the one party, and calumniate the other; <hi>&amp; vice verſa,</hi> as<note n="(w)" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> in his Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Hills</hi> third reaſon. p. 103.</note> Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> gives inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Seminary of Preiſts in his time, to make the diviſion of Proteſtants and Puritanes (as they call them) more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to the ſervice of Popiſh deſignes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If you have to deale with a Puritane</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall) you muſt ſay, truly Brother for you there is more hope then for theſe that be Proteſtants; becauſe they for feare of the Prince, and the Law are ready to ſay and beleeve any thing, and therefore me thinketh they be Atheiſts, but for you there is more hope, being either hot or cold. If you deale with a Proteſtant, tell him there is more hope of him then of the raſh brained Puritanes, becauſe they with Religion have put off all humanity &amp; civility with all other good manners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though ſome particular litigants in conteſtation for their cauſe and party, have been carryed by precipitation of paſſion to the expreſſion of much perſonall ſpight and reproach both in ſpeech and in print; yet <hi>the greatneſſe</hi> of the hazard to which both the one and the other will be expoſed, if their difference ſhould be driven on to a Military march, ſhould make them lay down their diſpleaſure, and take up the reſolution of the <hi>Roman</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Non me impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diant privatae offenſiones quo minus pro Reip. ſalute etiam cum inimieiſſimo conſentiam. Ci. cer. Epiſt. ad Plancum, Ep. Tom. l. <hi>10</hi> p. <hi>113.</hi>
                  </note> Oratour, <hi>No private offences or fallings out ſhall binder me, or make me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>leſſe ready to joyne with my greateſt enemy for the ſafety of the publick.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65388:19"/>
            <head>The third part of the Atteſtation, Containing an Apology for publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Errors, and for the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> in hand againſt the ſcandall of them, and of other impious and abſurd aberrations from Religion and reaſon charged upon it.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>TO this our confeſſion with you, we think fit by way of Apology for you and for our ſelves to add a caution againſt miſconceipt, which many perhaps take up upon the great noiſe and outcry we make againſt errors, &amp;c. <hi>which</hi>
                  <note n="(y)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>I. Goodw.</hi> Sion Colledge Viſited. p. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome thinke</hi> ſhould rather have been ſuppreſt with filence, <hi>then blazed ahroad to publick view, without an antidote againſt them, or refutation of them.</hi> And it is as probable, yea it is certaine to ſome of us who have heard it ſpoken, that all the reproaches of theſe impious opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, are caſt upon the Reformation in hand. To take off ſuch imputations we thinke it fit to ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Though problematicall errours which are preſented with ſome appearance of truth and reaſon, ſhould not be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed without diſproofe, becauſe by ſuch men may more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be deceived; Yet ſuch groſſe and as well abſurd as impious paradoxes, as moſt of the errors, &amp;c. in your Catalogue may be mentioned without particular confutation of them, as is the herefie of the <hi>Sadduees,</hi> who ſay, there is <hi>no reſurrection neither An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell nor ſpirit, Acts</hi> 23.8. and the herefie of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus ſaying,</hi> in the Apoſtles time, <hi>the Reſurrection, is paſt already,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17. and the blaſphemy of <hi>Rabſhekeh, Iſa.</hi> 36. from ver. 12. to the 20. which was heard at firſt without ſpeaking of a word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and that by an expreſſe command from King <hi>Hazeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> ver. 21. and afterwards thrice written without a refutation, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18. from v. 27. to v. 35. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 32.17, 18, 19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 36. foreci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, neither are ſuch irreligious and irrationall conceits or ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65388:20"/>worthy of a <hi>refutation,</hi> nor they who hold or vent them capable of a religious and rationall conviction.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Though in reſpect of others that may be required and performed, yet it is not requifite that every time they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported they ſhould be refuted, becauſe that hath either been done before, or may be done after in time convenient;<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pleniſſlmam habebis a nobis adverſus omnes haereſes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan. praefat. in l. c. adv. haereſ. p. <hi>228.</hi>
                  </note> Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>did not only rebearſe a large Catalogue of</hi> 80. <hi>hereſies, but (as he ſaith himſelfe) made a copious contradiction or confutation againſt them all.</hi> But<note n="(a)" place="margin">Aug. princ. Tom. <hi>6.</hi> operum.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing a Catalogue of hereſies after him did there only repeat and not refute them, though elſewhere hee ſpent a great deale of profitable paines in confutation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular hereſies and heretickes, as of the <hi>Manichees</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and many of them in particular, in his firſt Tome, and (in his ſixth Tome) of the <hi>Manichees</hi> in generall, and in particular of <hi>Priſcillianiſts, Origeniſts,</hi> and <hi>Arians,</hi> and in the ſeventh Tome of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> both in generall and particular. So that what is not done in your Catalogue, may if it bee needfull be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at another time; if not performed already by ſome other.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, Though thoſe who are not verſed in antiquities, thinke the errours which are now broached, eſpecially the abſurdeſt of them, to be new horne brats of the preſent age, yet, as in Philoſophie ſome are miſtaken (who take <hi>Copernicus</hi> for the firſt author of that giddy fancy, of the earths turning round, and the heavens ſtanding ſtill<note n="(b)" place="margin">Abrah. Bucolzerus Jud. Chronologicus. p. <hi>424.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for be was not borne till the yeer</hi> 1473. <hi>after Chriſt;</hi> and long before Chriſt it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to <hi>Nicetas</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Nicetas Syracuſius, (ut ait Theophraſtus,) coelum, ſolem, lunam, ſtellas, ſupra denique omnia ſtare cenſet, neque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer terram, remullam in mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do moveri. Cicer. Acad. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u. lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>26.</hi> fine.</note> 
                  <hi>Syracuſius,</hi>) ſo in Divinity, thoſe hereſies which ſeem the neweſt, &amp; of the lateſt hatch, have been both taught and contradicted, many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeers agoe, as that in the late moſt hereticall &amp; moſt impious Pamphlet of the <hi>Mortality of the ſoul,</hi> of the <hi>body of Chriſt aſcending no higher then the globe of the Sunne, and there arreſted untill the generall reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection;</hi> though many take it to be a new fiction of the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Writer in his booke of Mans Mortality, both ſoule and body. p. 33. printed 1643.</note> Writer thereof, never heard of before his time; yet the ſame was the tenet of the <hi>ancient</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Chriſtum cum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lum aſcenderit, corpus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um reliquiſſe in globo ſolis, hinc Manichaeos eſſe perſuaſtos ut ſolem adorarent. Sixt. Senenſ. Biblieth. Sanct. l. <hi>5.</hi> amot. <hi>140.</hi> p. <hi>381.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Manichees, and therefore they worſhipped the ſunne, becauſe they conceived the body of Chriſt was lodged in the globe thereof;</hi> and being ancient errours, they have met with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65388:20"/>their confutation heretofore many of them by <hi>Tertul. Iren. Epiphan. Aug.</hi> of old, and of later times, by <hi>Alphonſ. a Caſtre,</hi> who wrote 14. bookes in rehearſall and refutation of them, which <hi>Feuardentius</hi> publiſhed ſince his death, with the addition of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hereſies more, either pretermitted by <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> or borne ſince his death, (as he profeſſeth) though both of them miſcall thoſe hereſies which are not.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It may fall out that the Reformation may be carryed on by ſome men with too vehement an antipathy,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Impugnant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus invicem, ſua propria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantes. Iren. adverſ. kaereſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. <hi>164.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>uttering each of them his owne opinion, in a way of contradiction to others,</hi> whereby while they ſhun one errour, they run into another, ſometimes moſt contrary to it, ſo<note n="(g)" place="margin">Feuardent. in annot. in iſta verba. Iren. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. haereſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi> p. <hi>170.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Arius</hi> took up his herefie out of an hatred of the quite contrary tenet, held by <hi>Sabellius;</hi> and <hi>Eutiches,</hi> his herefie out of too paſſionate an oppofition to that of <hi>Neſtorius:</hi> and in like ſort out of an extreame deteſtation of the Domination of <hi>Prelacie,</hi> have many among us fallen to <hi>Independency,</hi> conceiving they could not be ſecure enough from Eccleſiaſticall tyranny, over their conſciencies, if there were any <hi>coercive power</hi> in one, as in the <hi>Epiſcopall,</hi> or in many, as in <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> government.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That the many errours, hereſies, and blaſphemies, which have ruſhed in upon us, in a kind of interregnum betwixt the pulling downe of the Prelaticall, and ſetting up the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall diſcipline, may not prejudice the preſent Reformation by the ſcandall which cometh from them, and the contumely which deſervedly belongeth to them; we are to bee remembred that it is no new thing, for the devill to beſtirre himſelfe as of late he hath done, to trouble, retard, and reproach the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by putting forth many falſe ones, which may puzzle the people, ſo that they know not which to betake themſelves to, but then eſpecially when any great change is to be made for the better. Which wee may obſerve in four moſt remarkable times and ſtates of Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>THe firſt was when Chriſtianity was to be ſet up, &amp; Judaiſme and Paganiſme to be preached downe, then did the Devill
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65388:21"/>diſpleaſed that his temples were deſerted, and Chriſt ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as under another title hath been noted, out of<note n="*" place="margin">Aug de civ. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>51.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>459.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aug. de civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate dei</hi>) raiſe up very many as impious, abſurd, and ridiculous opinions as any are taught in our times; as to begin with that wherein the Apoſtles lived, there was <hi>Simon Magus</hi> a beleever for a time, and one that was baptized by <hi>Philip, Acts</hi> 8.13. who pretended<note n="(h)" place="margin">Epiph. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> haereſ. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that his Concubine</hi> Helena <hi>was the ſame</hi> Helen <hi>of</hi> Greece, <hi>whom</hi> Homer <hi>wrote of, that ſhe made the Angels, and that the Angels made the world; that the Old Teſtament was not of God, and that it was a mortall ſin to beleeve it.</hi> He held another opinion<note n="(i)" place="margin">Semen viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum per deſlux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem faeminarum per conſuetos menſer collectum eſſe myſteria vis tae, cognitioniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que perfectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. ibid.</note> as impure as theſe were impious, which we conceive fitter to be ſet downe in the margin in Lat. then in this text in the Engliſh tongue. And we read of the Sect of the <hi>Nicolaitans, Rev.</hi> 2.6.15. deſcended from <hi>Nicolas</hi> a Proſelyte of <hi>Antioch,</hi> one of the ſeven Deacons choſen and appointed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6, 7. <hi>whoſe doctrine and practiſe</hi> had a rank ſavour of carnall ſinfulneſſe. And though for <hi>Nicolas</hi> himſelf, it be ſomewhat uncertain what to reſolve of him, for modeſty or immodeſty either in his dictates or doings, becauſe while ſome as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Nicol unus de <hi>7.</hi> diaconis cum intemperantiae domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari non poſſit, ut haberet quo petulantes affectus defenderet, docuit niſi quis ſingulis diebus uxorem exerceret, non poſſe participem fieri vitae aeternae. Epiph. ibid. haereſ. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and<note n="(l)" place="margin">Nicolaus Antiochenus omnlum mundiciarum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertor, choros duxit faeminarum Hieron. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>256.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> have accuſed him of very unclean opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and practices; others as<note n="(m)" place="margin">Clemens Alexand. Stromat. l. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>187.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and<note n="(n)" place="margin">Euſeb. Eccleſiaſt. hiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> have pleaded for him, <hi>that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing charged with jealouſie, having a beautiful wife, he brought her forth, and permitted him that liſted to marrie her;</hi> and<note n="(o)" place="margin">Monuerat Nicolaus Diaconus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> abuti carne: quo breviter dicto votupratem cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinum, maxime verd veneris, reprimendam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus voluit. <hi>Mr. Selden</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Gent. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi> p. <hi>9. the words in greek are in</hi> clem. Alexan. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. <hi>187.</hi> par. med.</note> a late learned authour, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending him, for that he taught <hi>the fleſh was to be abuſed, by which he meant that concupiſcence of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, eſpecially venercous, was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained:</hi> Yet is it not denied by any of the Authors who ſpeak ſo favourably of him, but that ſome of the ſame age, or not long after, tooke up licentious and laſcivious opinions in his name, and made their practice as looſe as their opinions<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>So</hi> Clemens Alexand. Euſeb. <hi>and</hi> Mr. Selden.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſo they ſinned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame in filthy fornication;</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Clemens Alexand. loco citat. lit. <hi>o.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>yea as</hi> Clemens Alexandrinus
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65388:21"/>
                  <hi>ſaith, they pronounced publicke Venery to bee a myſticall communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After them came up a moſt horrid and filthy Sect of the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi> whoſe impieties and impurities cannot bee mentioned without horror, and we therefore ſet them in the margin, and<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xores habuerunt Communes, impudica feminarum &amp; virorum contrectatio, nota fuit ejuſdem profeſſionis in Religione, Synaxim ipſam turpitudine multiplicis coitus polluerunt comedentes humanas carnes, vir conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens alteriuxorem, Surge dixit, fac dilectionem cum fratre. Turpiſſimam commixtionem ſecuta eſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, nam muliercula, itemq, vir fluxum a maſculo in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prias manus ſuſcipientes, coelum intuentes, dixerunt; Tibi pater hoc donum corpus Chriſti offerimus, &amp; ſic ipſum ederunt, aſſumentes ſemen ſuum, dixerunt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hoc eſt corpus Chriſti, hoc eſt paſcha. Epiph. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> haeroſ. <hi>26.</hi> Voluptatis gratia tantum, non generationis liberorum coierunt; hinc ſi quae praegnans facta ſuerit mulier, faetum in Mortario piſtillo contuderunt, &amp; admixto melle &amp; pipere participes facti ſunt, manibus turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinis ſuae defluxu imbutis, nudi toto corpore precati ſunt. Haec Epiph de Gnoſticis. ibid.</note> in <hi>Latine,</hi> for they are too groſſe to be put downe in plaine <hi>Engliſh;</hi> though thoſe who are wiſe, of ſuch a deadly poyſon, may make an wholeſome medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine to themſelves, inferring from ſuch premiſſes, that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there is a devil, for none but a ſpirituall impoſtor of great art and ſubtilty, as he is <hi>Acts</hi> 13.10. and of great power, as 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. could perſwade men to any ſuch prodigious impieties, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant not only to the law of Scripture, but to the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and thence muſt neceſſarily follow that there is a good God much greater and mightier then he, otherwiſe the whole world would run mad with ſuch Diabolicall deluſions. The <hi>Carpocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> heretickes were brethren to the <hi>Gnoſtickes</hi> according to the fleſh, whoſe impure impieties<note n="(s)" place="margin">Chriſti animam, &amp; quamlibet aliam, quae per omnes actiones turpes progreſſa eſt, poſſe in mundi factores &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos tranſire, unde multi ſeipſos ipſo Jeſu praeſtantiores profeſſi ſunt, exercuerunt magiam, incantationes &amp; alia Satanica opera. Epiph. ibid. haereſ <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> we will lap up in the ſame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; yet as<note n="(t)" place="margin">Chriſtianos ſenominarunt in Eccleſiae Chriſti opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; gentium ſcandalum. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiph.</hi> ſaith, <hi>they called themſelves Chriſtians, to the great ſcandall both of Chriſt and of the Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Adamites</hi> had ſome affinity with the former ſects, but they were more fooliſh then filthy, at leaſt in their filthineſſe not ſo ſhameleſſe, for as<note n="(v)" place="margin">Epiph. ibid. haereſ. <hi>52.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> writeth of them; they were like unto Mouldwarpes, who ſeldome appeared in the ſight of men, they held their males to be as <hi>Adam,</hi> and their females as <hi>Eve,</hi> in the ſtate of innocency, and therefore they excerciſed their Religion (ſuch as it was) in ſtoves and hot-houſes, naked, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65388:22"/>their cloths in an outward roome; if any man had any blemiſh, they caſt him out of their congregation calling him <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> who had eaten the forbidden fruit.<note n="(w)" place="margin">Epiph. ibid. haereſ. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>There was another</hi> ſort of heretickes called<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Ophis</hi> a Serpent.</note> 
                  <hi>Ophites</hi> from <hi>Ophis</hi> a ſerpent, for they worſhipped the Serpent that deceived <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> as a moſt wiſe creature endowed with all kind of knowledge.<note n="(y)" place="margin">Epiph. ibid. haereſ. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And ſome thought</hi> as well of <hi>Cain,</hi> whom they accounted their father, holding he was a man of more vigorous vertue then <hi>Abell,</hi> becauſe he was able to kill him; to him they ſorted<note n="(z)" place="margin">Epiph. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſau, Core, the Sod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mites</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> and in them they gloried as in their kinſmen, and aſeribed to them perfect and ſupernall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and for <hi>Judas</hi> they praiſed him for betraying of Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> ſome of them rendring for a reaſon that Chriſt was about to diſſolve things well eſtabliſhed, and others, that by betraying him to death, he did a good worke conducible to humane ſafety. Beſides theſe tenets peculiar to their ſect, they taught with the <hi>Corpocratians</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Epiph. ibid.</note> that none could be ſaved, unleſſe hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted every filthy act, calling upon a particular Angell, to whom they attribute the inſtinct of every particular ſinne on earth.</p>
               <p>We will conclude the hereſies raiſed by Satan againſt the firſt Reformation of Religion, from <hi>Judaiſme</hi> and <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> with the hereſie of the <hi>Pepuſians</hi> (omiting divers others, either leſſe odious, or leſſe ridiculous)<note n="(b)" place="margin">Epiph. ibid. haereſ. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> who fondly conceived upon a pretended revelation to <hi>Quintillus</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> that their City <hi>Pepuza</hi> in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> was the celeſtiall <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> foreſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Prophets; they likewiſe commended <hi>Eve</hi> for taſting the forbidden fruit, as a prudent act, and as the cauſe of our ſalvation; with them the word <hi>Saeerdos</hi> was practically as wel as grammatically of both genders, for women were admitted to all Eccleſiaſticall offices, and they alleadged for their promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous practiſe, (eſpecially for to make Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments) <hi>Miriam</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 15.20. and the foure daughters Propheteſſes of <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.8, 9. and that of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians, there is neither</hi> Iew <hi>nor</hi> Greeke, <hi>there is neither bondnor free, there is neither</hi> Male <hi>nor</hi> Female, <hi>for ye are all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Gal. 3.28.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65388:22"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond moſt inconſiderable time or ſtate of Religion was at the reformation and change of it from Popery to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy (by the Miniſtery of <hi>Luther, Calvin, Bucer, Beza</hi> &amp; others) then did the Devill to diſgrace it, ſet up ſundry graceleſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as <hi>John Islebius</hi> the father of the late <hi>Antinomians,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the uſe of the Law in the time of the Goſpel, and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Statuunt quaecunque tandem ſit hominis vita, quantum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis impura, juſtificari tamen eum ſi promiſſionibus evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galii credar. Sletdan. Comment. l. <hi>12.</hi> p. <hi>248.</hi>
                  </note> held <hi>that how impure ſoever a mans life be, yet be is juſtified if he beleeve the promiſes of Chriſt;</hi> and<note n="(d)" place="margin">Bell. Chronol. part. altera. p. <hi>567.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who being but 25. yeers of age, bragged that hee was the chiefe Prophet of the world; when as the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Servetus non ſimplicem, ſed ex multis impietatibus conflatam haereticorum larvam profitetur, puta, Arii, Marcionis, &amp;c. Paſtores Eccleſiae Baſileenſ. Epiſt. Syndicis &amp; Senatui inter Calvin. Epi ſtol. p. <hi>127.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>paſters of the Church of Baſil,</hi> ſhew hee profeſſed not the errours of any ſimple or ſingular heretick, but a compound of the hereſies of <hi>Arius, Marcion, Sabellius, Photinus, Manichaeus,</hi> and <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> and divers of the Church of<note n="(f)" place="margin">Reſuſcitat nobis Priſcillianos, Anthropomorphitas, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollinariſtas, Valentinianos. Miniſtr. Eecleſ. Bern. Syndic. &amp; Senatui Genev. ibid. p. <hi>118.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Berne</hi> charge him with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving other hereſies. And the Divines of <hi>Tigure</hi> objected to him<note n="(g)" place="margin">Trinitatem aternam Deitriceps Monſtrum &amp; Cerbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quendam tripartitum; denique imaginarios Deos illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones ac tres Spiritus daemoniorum appellitat. Miniſtr. Tigur. Eccleſ. Syndie. &amp; Senatui Genev. ibid. p. <hi>120.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>moſt execrable blaſpbemies</hi> againſt the ſacred Trinity, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> which he wrote<note n="(h)" place="margin">Bellar. Chronol. par. altera. p. <hi>567.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſeaven b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>phemous</hi> bookes.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the Devill ſtirred up one<note n="(i)" place="margin">Bell. ibid. p. <hi>569.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>David George,</hi> who tooke upon him to be a great Prophet, and the elder brother of Chriſt, and promiſed that three years after his death he would riſe again, and reſtore the Kingdom unto <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> There was alſo one<note n="(k)" place="margin">Bellarm. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Caſper Swbenckeſeldius</hi> a <hi>Sileſian,</hi> who held, that upon the aſcenſion of Chriſt into heaven the humane nature was turned into the Divine;<note n="(l)" place="margin">Litera mortua, egenum eleme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſic Hoſius, de expreſſoverbe Dei, paulo ante med. non diſting. capit. Sect. nec figure.</note> and <hi>that the Scripture was but a dead letter, a beggerly element.</hi> There was alſo one <hi>Muneo</hi> who (as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith of him) <hi>ſet forth an haereſie drawne out of the dotages of the</hi> Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65388:23"/>concerning the nature and perſon of Chriſt.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Liquet te ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſum eſſe &amp; conatum ſparge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re haereticam doctrinam, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemiis plenam, contra ſacrum Myſterium Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis. Calv. o. puſc. p. <hi>671.</hi>
                  </note> And another named <hi>Valentinus Gentilis</hi> a blaſphemous here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke againſt the ſacred Trinity, againſt whom the <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicks</hi> of <hi>Geneva</hi> proceeded to a judiciall Sentence for a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and ſubmiſſive recantation of his tenets. But there were <hi>two ſorts of heretickes</hi> which moſt defamed the Reformation of Religion in thoſe dayes, the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Sleid. Com. l. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>116.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Libertines:</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> denyed the baptiſme of infants to bee lawfull; and taught that if they were baptized, ſuch baptiſme was a nullity; they held a Communitie of goods, bragged of Revelations by viſions and dreames; whereupon at <hi>Sangall</hi> in <hi>Helvetia</hi> one<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> cut off his brothers head in the preſence of his parents, to which he was perſwaded (as he ſaid) that he was commanded by God himſelfe. Of this Sect the head as a King and a Prophet was<note n="(o)" place="margin">Sleid. ib. l. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>200.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>John Leyden,</hi> who taught that a man was not bound by marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to one woman, but might be allowed as many wives as hee pleaſed and for this (when ſome Doctors oppoſed his opinion) hee threw downe his cloake, and the New Teſtament on the ground, and ſwore by them both, that the Doctrine he delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red was revealed to him from heaven.</p>
               <p>With him propheſied <hi>Knipperdoling,</hi> a blaſphemous brain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke Heretick, who ſaid he had received it from heaven,<note n="(p)" place="margin">Sleid. ibid. p. <hi>199.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that all Temples</hi> ſhould be deſtroyed, and preſently the beſotted peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fell to worke, as he gave out the word,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>201.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and when</hi> a great crowd of people ſtood below him, ſtanding upon an aſcent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their head, hee went upon their heads with his hands and his knees, breathing upon them, and ſaying, <hi>the Father hath ſanctified thee, receive the holy-Ghoſt;</hi> and to deceive the people yet further with more apparent danger, up ſtart a new prophet a <hi>Gold-ſmith</hi> by his calling, (his name is not noted) but a <hi>Black-ſmith</hi> or <hi>Iron-ſmith</hi> rather by his ſpeech, and hee boldly denounced as a dictate of the heavenly Father<note n="(r)" place="margin">Sleid. ibid. p. <hi>200.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>John Leiden</hi> muſt bee Emperour of the whole world, and that being aſſiſted with ſtrong forces hee ſhould without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or exception, kill all Kings and Princes, and ſhould ſpare only the multitude, to wit, thoſe that love juſtice, and ſo hee ſhould poſſeſſe the ſeat of his father <hi>David,</hi> untill his father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it again.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65388:23"/>
               <p>The other notorious and dangerous Sect, prejudiciall to the honour and progreſſe of the Reformation begun, was the Sect of the <hi>Libertines,</hi> of whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> having made a very ſhort and inſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eport intitles it to <hi>Calvin,</hi> and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe his extream contempt of him, he<note n="(*)" place="margin">Quorum non alium authorem habeo niſi Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannem Calvin. haereſiarcham. Bellarm. Chron. par. ult. p. <hi>371.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>excuſeth himſelfe that bee hath no other author of the</hi> Libertine <hi>tenents, then</hi> John Calvin <hi>the heretiark in his booke againſt the</hi> Libertines: but though to him the name of <hi>Calvine</hi> be ignominious, and to other Papiſts, whom malice hath made mad againſt him, (as <hi>Saul</hi> againſt the Saints before he was converted <hi>Acts</hi> 26.11. ſo deſpicable as to<note n="(s)" place="margin">Alii ſuis cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Calvini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men imponunt. Melch. Adam. paſtor. decad. vitar. Theolog. p. <hi>82.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>put the name of</hi> Calvin <hi>upon their Dogs;</hi> to us and to all ſound and ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Proteſtants, it is (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of a good name) <hi>better then pretious oyntment, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. and his diſcovery of the opinions and manners of the <hi>Libertines,</hi> the more authenticke, and the more punctually to be related, becauſe hee is the exacteſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their ſtory, ſpeaketh of his owne knowledge of them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had perſonall notice of, and conteſtation with the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of that ſinfull ſect<note n="(t)" place="margin">Calvin. Inſtr. adverſ. Libert. c. <hi>4.</hi> opuſc. p. <hi>436.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quintine</hi> and <hi>Poiquius;</hi> there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo one <hi>Coppine,</hi> whom the devill ſet up before the former of theſe two, to begin the ſowing of the <hi>Libertine</hi> tares, but his fame was ſoone obſcured by <hi>Quintine,</hi> and his memory in a manner buried by his proceeding and prevailing.</p>
               <p>His diſcourſe of them is ſomewhatlarge, taking up about 17. leaves in folio, but we will contract what is pertinent to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe into a narrower com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe: <hi>In the generall</hi>
                  <note n="(v)" place="margin">Adverſ. fanaticam &amp; furioſam Sectam Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinor. qui ſe ſpirituales vocant. <hi>So in the title of his Inſtr.</hi> p. <hi>433.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>hee calls them a furious and fanaticke Sect, who call themſelves ſpirituall,</hi> and yet<note n="(w)" place="margin">Vt ſcelerata Secta, ita longe aliis magis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digioſa &amp; belluina eſt, adeo ut nemo ſana mente praeditus ſine horrore de ea cogitare poſſit. ibid. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>434.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>are prodigiouſly wicked, and brutiſh, ſo that no man that is well in his wits, can thinke of what they hold without horrour,</hi> and ſo foule and filthy<note n="(x)" place="margin">Eorum Secta cloaca eſt aut ſentina quaedam in quam omnes ſordes confluunt. ib. c. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>456.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that it is as the common receptacle of all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> In particular they blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly confounded God and man in their operations and actions,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Cum aliquando Quintinus in locwn veniſſet ubi quidam interfectus jacebat, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illic adeſſet ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis vir pius, qui prae horrore diceret, hei mihi quis hocſcelus admiſit? putidus ille inquis. Ita res haber, tu ipſe admiſiſti, ego admiſi, Deus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit, quod enim ego &amp; tu ſacimus, Deus efficit, quod etiam Deus facit ipſi facimus, nam in nebis eſt. Ibid. c. <hi>13.</hi> p. <hi>445.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that what God did, they did, what they did, God did, whatſoever it was,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65388:24"/>though a murder or any ſuch crime becauſe God was in them:</hi>
                  <note n="(z)" place="margin">Hoc conceſſe imputandun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſet Deo peccatum, aut con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludendum nullum in mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do peccatum fieri — unde ſequetur nobis non licere aliquid ut malum vitupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>this granted, all ſinne muſt bee imputed unto God, or it muſt bee concluded that there is no ſinne in all the world, becauſe there is nothing which God doth not;</hi> and thence alſo it followeth, <hi>that nothing is to bee blamed as evill, and that a man following his own inclination</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Concupivit uxorem vicini ſui quiſpiam, ea potiatur ſi poteſt, certo enim ſcit, ſe nibil a voluntate Dei alienum facere, ib p. <hi>445.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>(ſuppoſe it be to lye with another mans wiſe) may doe it.</hi> And <hi>therein be doth nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the will of God</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Fiert omnia ex voluntate Dei, nibil ipſi diſplicere. ibid. c. <hi>15.</hi> p. <hi>448.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>who is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with nothing that man doth.</hi> As for the devill and ſinne,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Diabolum &amp; peccatum accipiunt pre ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatione, quae nibil eſt. ibid. p. <hi>444.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>they take them for a meer imagination, which is nothing.</hi> For Chriſt they ſet up an<note n="(d)" place="margin">Proplaſtice Chriſtum fingunt qui non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum idolum ſit adverſus filium Dei, ſed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti ſordium omnium ſaccus, aut cloaca in quam faeces omnetre cipiantut. ib. p. <hi>450.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Idoll Figment</hi> of their owne, and make <hi>him the ſack or ſinke of all impure dregs.</hi> And indeed they put<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ipſi Chriſto probrum inurant quo Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo deterior cenſeri poſſit. ib. c. <hi>4</hi> p. <hi>437.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſo much repreach upon him, as may make him worſe then the Devill himſelfe.</hi> For the <hi>ſacred</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">Aperte ridere ſoliti ſunt, ſi quis ſcripturas allegaret: nec diffimulare quin eas pro fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis haberent. Calv. Inſtruct. adv. Libert. c. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>441.</hi> col. <hi>1.2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scriptures</hi> if any cited them againſt their hereticall and prophane o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, <hi>they derided them, accounting no better of them then of fables;</hi> and to ſhew themſelves lawleſſe <hi>Libertines,</hi> they will have it;<note n="(g)" place="margin">Totam legem abolere volunt, inquientes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llam amplius ejus habendam eſſe rationem, propterea quod in libertatem aſſerti ſimus. ibid. c. <hi>19.</hi> p. <hi>453.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that the whole Law is aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ſo as now it is no more to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>becauſe</hi> (as they argue) <hi>wee are put into a ſtate of perfect liberty.</hi> And how little reſpect they had of the Goſpel, is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by their contemptuous ſpeeches of the Apoſtles,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Apud eos Paulus vas confractum erat, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus abnegator Dei, Johannes adoleſcens ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidus, Matthaeus faenerator. ibid. c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>435.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>calling</hi> Paul <hi>a broken veſſell,</hi> Peter <hi>a Runnegado from God,</hi> Iohn <hi>a fooliſh young man,</hi> Matthew an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer.</hi> And rejecting the bonds of the Law, and guidance of the Goſpel, they let looſe the reins to their lewdeſt luſts, according to their pernicious principle, which is<note n="(i)" place="margin">Quod omnis hominum inclinatio ſive a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura, ſive a maſa conſue tudine proficiſcatur, vooatio Dei eſt. ibid. c. <hi>20.</hi> p. <hi>455.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that every inclination of man, whether it be of nature, or of cuſtome, is the calling of God;</hi> and therefore if<note n="(k)" place="margin">Simulatque adulter ſcortatoris ſui taedium caeperit, eum ſubinde commutare poteſi ſi quis alius magis grat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſeſe offerat. Similiter ſcortator. &amp;c. ibid. c. <hi>20.</hi> p. <hi>455.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>an adultereſſe</hi> be weary of, or not well
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65388:24"/>pleaſed with her fleſhly bed-fellow, ſhe may change for another, who may bee more acceptable to her; and an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer or Fornicator hath the like liberty for female variation; and<note n="(l)" place="margin">Leno, inquiunt, fungatur munere ſuo, fur au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacter furetur, eſt enim conſentanenm ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, ut unuſquiſque vocationem ſuam ſequatur. ibid. c. <hi>20.</hi> p. <hi>454.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>if any have been imployed as a Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or a Baude, or a thiefe, they may hold on their courſe, becauſe it is their calling. The</hi>
                  <note n="(m)" place="margin">In bona confuſionem inducunt, communione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sanctorum eſſe dicentes, ſi nemo quicquam poſſideat tanquam ſuum, ſe dunuſquiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nanciſci poterit ad ſe rapiat. ibid. c. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>455.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>confuſion of goods, they called the communion of Saints,</hi> and permitted every man to get what he could by what way ſoever unto himſelfe. And ſo they allowed themſelves and all their ſort a<note n="(n)" place="margin">Hocu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um eſt ex praecipuis capitibus Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiae ipſorum, artem ſimulandi &amp; ſeſe transformundi noſſe oportere, quo facilius hominibus imponant — qua ſibi permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt omnem ſpeciem induere quo placeant ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus. ibid. c. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>440.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>liberty</hi> to diſſemble any thing with any man, in any matter, whereby they might deceitfully inſinuate themſelves into their good opinion, and ſo they made no ſcruple<note n="(o)" place="margin">Nulla eſt ipſis religio, coram Idolis ſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternere, ita ſe omnibns ſuperſtitionibus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtarum adhaerere ſe ſimulant. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>to adore Idolls, nor to adhere to all the ſuperſtitions of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> no nor blaſphemouſly to fiatter them in the abominable idolatry of the Maſſe: for <hi>Quintine</hi> himſelfe being once preſent where<note n="(p)" place="margin">Cum aliquando Quintinus ſolenni cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Cardinalis Miſſae adeſſet dicebat ſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam Dei videre. ibid. c. <hi>20.</hi> p. <hi>454.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> a Cardinall ſaid Maſſe, profeſſed <hi>that at that time be ſaw the glory of God.</hi> And though for ſuch partly Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall, and partly brutiſh deceipts and dealings they were ſuch as <hi>Calvin</hi> well ſaith were worthy <hi>that</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Omnes ad pueros uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſos conſpuere infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem pratereuntium deberent, ut hoc execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſigno pudore afficerent cos. ibid. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. <hi>437.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>all even to children ſhould ſpit at them, in token of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration as they paſſed by, that they might make them aſbamed;</hi> thouſands<note n="(r)" place="margin">Multis animarum millibus exitii cauſa fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt. ibid.</note> of ſouls were ſeduced by them to their deſtruction, the particular account they reckoned to is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Ganeones aut tres ſaltem video qui plus quam <hi>4</hi> millia hominum in exitium duxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. ibid. c. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>436.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>foure thouſand,</hi> an argument of the ſingular ſubtilty of Satan, and of the great ſimplicity, or rather groſſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity of the people; and withall an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Divine indignation, as<note n="(t)" place="margin">Certrſſimum illud eſt exundantis in mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum furoris Dei flagellum, cum couſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae habenas laxetut tam deteſtanda quae, lli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſtianis perſuadeant, quae prophanis ipſis horrorem incutiant. Calv. Epiſt. Ep. N. N. p. <hi>222.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> elſewhere ſaith, <hi>in letting out the chaine of Satan ſo many linkes, as that he ſhould be able to perſwade Chriſtians to beleeve and receive
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65388:25"/>ſuch dictates as would ſtrike a horror in the hearts of prophane men when they heare them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe third conſiderable time and ſtate of Religion was then, when divers godly Divines and other well-affected Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians deſired and indeavoured a further conformity with other reformed Churches in diſcipline, and ceremonies in the reign of Queen</hi> Elizabeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of this</hi>
                  <note n="(v)" place="margin">Camd. Hiſt. Q. Eliz. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>90.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſaith</hi> Camden, <hi>in the 11th of her reign</hi> Colman, Button, Hattingham, Benſon, <hi>and others who with burning zeale profeſſing a more ſincere Religion, allowed of nothing but what was drawn from the fountains of the holy ſcriptures— they openly called in queſtion</hi> the received diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Liturgie and the vocation of Biſhops, yea they condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them as ſavouring too much of the Romiſh Religion, (with which to have any communion they cryed out was impious) uſing all the meanes they could that all things in the Church of <hi>England</hi> might he reformed according to the rule of the Church of <hi>Geneva;</hi> of theſe men he further adds, that though the Queen commanded they ſhould be committed to priſon, yet incredible it is, how much the followers of this Sect increaſed every where, through a certaine obſtinate wilfullneſſe in them, indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Biſhops, and the ſecret favour of ſome noble men, which gaped ofter the wealth of the Church, which ſort began preſently to be knowne by the invious name of <hi>Puritanes; ſo farre he, too farre for a true Hiſtorian, who (if he would needs give reaſons of their accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the people) ſhould and might have given others of a far better reliſh to religious palates. And for the name</hi> Puritane <hi>which he familiarly miſapplyeth, it belongeth rather unto thoſe who would have the Church to be thought ſo pure, that it was not needfull to reforme it, then to thoſe who diſcovered the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and faults of it, and deſired it might be a graduate to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to a further degree of goodneſſe, then the firſt aſſayes of Reformation could reach unto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was afterwards proſecuted further by the penners of the admonition to the Parliament,</hi> An. <hi>1573. and by Mr.</hi> Cartwrights <hi>defence of it againſt Dr.</hi> Whitgift, <hi>as by their Polemicall writings
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65388:25"/>is evident, ſet forth by the Dr. in the year 1574. and Mr.</hi> Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrights <hi>reply unto him in two parts; the firſt,</hi> An. <hi>1575. the 2d.</hi> An. <hi>1577.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to hinder it (as Mr</hi> Joſias Nio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls <hi>who was a mover for it, a man of good learning, godly life, and of a gratious and meek ſpirit, obſerveth)</hi>
                  <note n="(w)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr. Ioſtas Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colls</hi> plea of the innocent. So in the contents of the 2. ch. nu. 2.</note> Martine Marprelate, <hi>the</hi> Browniſts, <hi>and</hi> Hacket <hi>were ſtirred up by Satan.</hi> More particularly hee<note n="(x)" place="margin">Ib. c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith the firſt was a fooliſh jeſter, who termed himſelfe <hi>Martin Marprelate</hi> and his ſons, who under counterfeit and apiſh ſcoffing did play the Sycophant, and ſlanderouſly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many perſons of reverent place and note, &amp; ſuch was the wiſedome of the time, that many filthy and lewd Pamphlets came forth againſt him, caſting forth much ſtinking dung and beaſtly filth into the faces of honeſt men,<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>33.</hi>
                  </note> ſo that it plainly apeared to the wiſer &amp; diſcreeter ſort, that the devill was the author of this diſgrace.<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Secondly, for the <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> they tooke offence at both ſides, and made a temerarious and wicked ſeparation; they had their originall and name ſaith<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cambd.</hi> Hiſt. of Q Eliz. l. 3. p. 257.</note> 
                  <hi>Camden</hi> from <hi>Robert Browne</hi> a <hi>Cambridge</hi> man a young ſtudent in Divinity, who condemning the Church of <hi>England</hi> as no Church entangled many in the ſnares of their new ſchiſme. Thirdly, of <hi>Hacket</hi> and his party,<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. Ioſ. Nic. lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co citat.</note> Mr. <hi>Nic.</hi> ſaith, two or three men bewitched with ſome honour, by a certaine man of a frantick ſpirit, lifted up themſelves with high words of blaſphemie, whoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this was all men know, that know the wiles of Satan. <hi>But that both may be better knowne, (for more aſſurance of this truth, and better caution againſt the ſlander of Religion) it wil be requifite to make a more clear and full report of the Diabolicall blaſphemie and furie of that impious Impoſtor</hi> Hacket, <hi>which we will make up out of the ſeverall relations of</hi> Camden <hi>and</hi> Seravia.<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Camd.</hi> Hiſt. of Q. Eliz. l. 4. p. 400.</note> This <hi>Hacket</hi> was a man of vulgar ſort, borne at <hi>Oundle</hi> in the Counly of <hi>Northampton,</hi> unlearned, inſolent, fierce, and ſo eager up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on revenge, that he bit off his honeſt Schoole-maſters noſe (as be imbraced him, under colour of renewing their love) and like a dog (as they ſay) eat
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65388:26"/>it downe before the poore deformed mans face, while he prayed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it to him, that it might be ſewed to whileſt the wound was green. And ſo averſe was hee from all piety that the heavenly doctrine which he had learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in Sermons, he repeated among his drinking companions at their cups to be derided. Afterward when he had waſted his eſtate which be had with a widow, be ſuddainly tooke upon him the perſon of one of admirable ſanctity, ſpent all his time in hearing Sermons, learning ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>and as the devill puts on an holy-day habit, transforming him into an angel of light, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>11.14.</hi> ſo did he preſent himſelfe in the appearance of an inſpired Saint, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wring forth his prayers with an admirable and ſtrange kind of ſervour; falling upon his face as wrapt in an extaſie, and expoſtulating as it were with God. But whereas all men are wont in calling upon God to implore his preſence, he only was accuſtomed to pray that God would abſent and withdraw himſelfe from the congregation of thoſe that were praying.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>401.</hi>
                  </note> He counterſeited <hi>revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made to him from heaven, by which he dignified himſelfe with the title of</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ibid.</note> King of <hi>Europe</hi> ordained by God. <hi>And his delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded diſciples</hi> Copinger <hi>and</hi> Arthrington <hi>added that hee was the higheſt and ſupream Monarch, &amp;</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>402.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that all the</hi> Kings of <hi>Europe</hi> did hold their Kingdomes of him, as his vaſſalls, that be alone therefore was to be obeyed, and the Queen depoſed. <hi>Beſides this temporall, hee aſſumed a ſpirituall preeminence of a very high degree, for he</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Ecoelo ab ipſo Spiritu ſancto unctus fun, Dr. Hadr. Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de grad. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtr. c. <hi>2</hi> p. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſaid</hi> he was anoynted from beaven by the holy Ghoſt; <hi>commanded his two Prophets, the one of mercy, the other of judgement,</hi> Coppinger <hi>and</hi> Arthrington, to<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ite, inquit, &amp; civibus Lond. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>unciate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Dominum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>coelis deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe cum venti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labro in manu ſua, ut judiceto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem. ibid.</note> proclaime in the City of <hi>London,</hi> that Chriſt the Lord <hi>(meaning himſelfe)</hi> was come from heaven with his ſan in his hand to judge the world; <hi>which hee averred with ſo much confidence</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Quod ſi quis vos roget ubi ſit, dicite cum eſſe in aedibus Walke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri in fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giportu; ſi cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere nolunt, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niant huc, &amp; me ſi poſſint occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. ibid.</note> that hee had them tell where he lodged, <hi>challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them that would not beleeve him,</hi> to come thither and kill him if they could. <hi>And when for his blaſphemous arrogance againſt God and his ſonne Chriſt Jeſus, and many ſeditious and diſloyall expreſſions of his ſpight and contempt of the Queen, he was brought to condigne and capitall puniſhment; while he was under the hands of the Executioner</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Blaſphemo ore Deo minitans niſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praeſens au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llium ei mitteres ibid. p. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> he was not afraid to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten God himſelfe, if hee did not ſend preſent helpe for his deliverance.<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caind</hi> Hiſt. of Q Eliz. p. 403.</note> Being condemned, hee was laid upon an hurdle and drawne to the chiefe ſtreet of the City, inceſſantly rearing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65388:26"/>out with a dreadfull ſound, Iehova Meſſias, behold the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the heaven open, behold the Sonne of the moſt High deſcending downe to deliver me. At the Gallowes being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to acknowledge his ſinne againſt God, and the Queen, the execrable wretch inveighing moſt contumeliouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the Queen, cryed out with a <hi>Stentors</hi> voice, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly God Almighty, Iehovah, Alpha and Omega, Lord of Lords, King of Kings, God everlaſting, thou knoweſt that I am the true Iehovah whom thou haſt ſent, ſhew ſome miracle out of the cloud, to convert theſe inſidells, and take me from mine enemies. But if not <hi>(I tremble to ſpeak it)</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Saith the forecited au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports it.</note> I will ſet the heavens on fire, and with theſe hands plucke thee out of thy throne: and other ſpeeches he uſed more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable. Turning him to the Hang-man as he was putting the rope to him, Thou Baſtard ſaid he wilt thou hang <hi>Hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket</hi> thy King? having the rope about his neck, he lift up his eyes, and grinning ſaid, Doſt thou repay mee this for a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? I come to revenge it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides theſe homebred perturbers of the progreſſe of Religion, in the way towards a more perfect reformation, there came ſome forainers from</hi> Holland <hi>a Countrey</hi> (<hi>as</hi> Camd. <hi>cenſures it</hi>) <hi>fruitfull</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Ibid p. <hi>218.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>of hereticks,</hi> who under a ſhew of ſingular integrity and ſanctity, inſinuated themſelves into the ignorant vulgar people, and then distilled into their mindes damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, mnifeſtly repugnant to the Chriſtian faith, by a porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous &amp; ſtrange kind of ſpeaking, moſt contrary to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion, which men might rather admire then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Theſe named themſelves the family of Love, or houſe of Charity. They perſwaded their followers that thoſe onely were elected and to be ſaved which were admitted into that family, and all the reſt reprobates and to be damned, and that it was lawfull for them to deny upon their oath before a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate whatſoever they liſt, or before any other which was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65388:27"/>not of their family: of this fanaticall vanity they diſperſed bookes among their followers, tranſlated out of the <hi>Dutch</hi> tongue into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which they entituled, the Goſpel of the Kingdome, Documentall ſentences, the prophecies of the ſpirit of Love, the publiſhing of peace upon earth. The Author <hi>H. N.</hi> whoſe name at length they cold by no means be perſwaded to reveal, yet it was found afterward to bee <hi>Henry Nicolai</hi> of <hi>Leiden.</hi> Who with blaſphemous mouth gave out, that hee did partake of God, and God of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>THe fourth State or time of Reformation, is that which at preſent is peſtered with ſo many errors, hereſies, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies: concerning which your Catalogue of them will ſave us the labour of the like account, which concerning others wee have brought in.</p>
               <p>From ſuch unſound Divinity, ſuch brain-ficke blaſphemie, ſuch a fruitfull harveſt of the Tares of hereſie, as have moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in theſe times (wherein Reformation was to be ſet up, and former ſwarvings from Religion and reaſon to be ſilenced and ſuppreſſed) will fairly follow that which may confirme our faith in the word of God, and may conforme our affections to a better liking of Religion, in that edition of it corrected and amended, which now is offered to the acceptance of all well-minded people. As</p>
               <p>Firſt, That herein we ſee by experience the proof of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles prediction, that <hi>there m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t be hereſies that thoſe which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be manifeſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. And that they alſo may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, who are <hi>toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine, Eph.</hi> 4.14. And in reſpect of ſome who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et themſelves againſt the truth, and ſettle their reſolutions to oppoſe it, that of the ſame Apoſtle may verified, <hi>God ſhall ſend them ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ions, that they ſhould beleeve a lye, that all might be damned which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That theſe hereſies are as the Apoſtle calls them the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65388:27"/>
                  <hi>Doctrines of Devills,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe many of them are ſo abſurdly impious, as to be clearly contradictorie to the light, not only of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but of humane nature.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe though many of them were ancient, yet hereticks of later times have revived them, not only by reading (for the leaders of many among them, were altogether i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iterate) but by the inſtinct of Satan, as<note n="(l)" place="margin">See <hi>Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> his 3. Ch. of his inſtr. adv. lib. p. 434, 435.</note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> well obſerveth, in his inſtruction againſt the <hi>Libertines</hi> of his time, who though they agreed with many of the ancient hereticks <hi>Cerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Marcion,</hi> the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and <hi>Manichees;</hi> yet<note n="(m)" place="margin">Hi quidem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines indocti ſunt ac idiotae, qui non uſque a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo evolvendis chartis funt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitati ut ex tis deliria ſua ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcere po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uerint nec veri ſimile eſt ipſos ſcire ullam unquam de his mentione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> babitam fuiſſe — ſed idem magiſter qui ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres illos haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos olim ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adem d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina iſtos im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buere p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teſt qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> illos inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. ibid. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>434.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> being unlearned idiots, as he calleth them, and not acquainted with bookes or writings, they did not draw their dotages from them, nor is it like they had any mention of them, but that the ſame maſter the devil who ſtirred up the hereticks of old, did inſtill the like doctrine into theſe new diſciples.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe he knoweth better then any <hi>Matchiovillian</hi> Politician how to make uſe of diviſion among men, eſpecially Chriſtians, to ſerve to his greateſt advantage, and his advantage is to make ſome of a wrong Religion, ſome to ſtand at a gaze as an ignorant travailer where many wayes meet, and to make choiſe of no Religion; and ſome who have miſchoſen the worſt, to reproach the beſt; not only by their expreſſe contumelies, but by their pernicious wayes, (their groſſe errors, and loofe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) by reaſon whereof, as <hi>Peter</hi> propheſied, <hi>the way of truth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vill ſpoken of,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. And from differences in opinion hee well knoweth how to breed diſike in affection, which if he can, he wil raiſe to the height of moſt hatefull hoſtility, as he did by the ſpirit of the <hi>Arians, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>natiſts, An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>baptiſts,</hi> and other hereticks both of the ancient and more recent times.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Since all ſound Chriſtians reſolved for the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that Chriſtianity was the right Religion, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme and Paganiſme the wrong, (notwithſtanding the many and monſtrous errors, &amp;c. in the primitive times) and that for the ſecond, the Proteſtant Religion is the right, and Popery the wrong Religion, though as impious errors brokeforth as before; ſo we may reſolve of the other two Reformations from <hi>Prelaecie</hi> to <hi>Presbyteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> from a cold and corrupt Liturgy, to a more cordiall
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65388:28"/>and ſincere ſervice of God, from the burden of ſuperſtitious ceremonies, to a true freedome of conſcience, and Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, (in the third deſired, and by the fourth in a good part performed) that they have the better cauſe who ſtood for them, and indeavoured to carry it on to perfect accompliſhment, not they that oppoſe it, albeit the Devill (as afore time) hath let out ſome ſmoake of errors, &amp;c. from the bottomleſſe pit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.2. to darken the light thereof, that it might not ſhine forth in ſo clear a conviction, and ſo effectuall a converſion as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it might doe; yet even this working of Satan (with all who are truly inſtructed in the principles and progreſſe of Religion, and are not ignorant of his deviſes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. is an argument that the reformation is of God, becauſe the devil uſeth ſuch ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and diligence, to defame and diſgrace it, and if he could to ſuppreſſe it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, If that be true which out of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>norus Reggus</hi> a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne writer wee have noted, that this laſt Reformation hath been inveſted with more and more prodigious errors, &amp;c. then any other, this alſo makes nothing to the prejudice of thoſe truths of doctrine, diſcipline, and worſhip, which now are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the world, but rather much for them, ſince of the later times, it is eſpecially prophecied, <hi>that men ſhould depart from the ſaith, and give heed to ſpirits of error, and doctrines of devils;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. which importeth an encreaſe of hereſies both in kind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of proficiency from bad to worſe in late ſucceeding more then in ancient foregoing ages.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> in his treanſe how to live, and that well. vol. 1. <hi>P.</hi> 479. col. 1.</note> Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> obſerving ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to this purpoſe, where he ſaith, <hi>that hereſies abound in this laſt age of the world,</hi> gives for a reaſon of it, the devils reviving of the hereſies of former ages, beſides the invention of ſome new ones; to which we may adde, that hee is the more buſie at this time, in proſecution of his deſigne for ſpreading of errors, &amp;c. (as more outragious in his wrath) becauſe his time is but ſhort, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12.</p>
               <p>If it be objected as by ſome it is,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> in favour of Prelacie, and for Prelation of it before Presbyterie out of the forementioned author, <hi>that whereas in foure yeers ſpace loſt paſt (wherein the Biſhops were oppoſed and depoſed) there have been ſuch multiplicity of monſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sects in</hi> England, <hi>as in ſo ſhort a time was never knowne in any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince;</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65388:28"/>and that there were in<note n="(o)" place="margin">Eipiſcoporum tempora intra <hi>60.</hi> annos non niſi <hi>4.</hi> Secta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> protulerunt, Puritanos, Browniſtas, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſtas, &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtas. Hon. Reg. de ſtat. Eccleſ. in Angl. p. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 60. years of the Biſhops but four Sects, <hi>Puritans, Browniſts, Familiſts,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> nay but three, for he ſaith thoſe that were called<note n="(p)" place="margin">Puritani erant viri pii &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i qui ab epiſcopis quod ad gubernatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, caeremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as &amp; ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones quasdam diſſentieban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ib.</note> 
                  <hi>Puritans,</hi> were <hi>godly &amp; ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox men, who in Church-government, ceremonies, and ſome ſuperſtitions diſſented from the Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> To this we anſwer, firſt, that the reporter being a ſtranger to our State, though converſant in many of our controverſiall wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings might bee miſtaken in the number of Sects among us, and doubtleſſe he was ſo, for beſide thoſe he nameth, there were <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Arminians, Socinians, Grindletonians, Hothoringtonians, Traſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, If there were fewer Sects in that longer, then in this leſſer time, it might be there was the more peace, leſſe diviſion, becauſe the ſtrong man armed kept the palace, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.21. For the Biſhops held their palaces armed with great power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and they were divers of them as willing as able, to doe the devill better ſervice then petty Sects could doe, for their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency at Court, in the Star-chamber, high Commiſſion, their croſſe keyes of order and juriſdiction, perſonall, and conſiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, enabled them to ſuſpend and ſilence the moſt conſcientious and powerfull Preachers, to put downe Lectures and afternoone Sermons on the Sabbath, and to ſet up carnall ſports and recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations on that day, to uphold non-reſidences, pluralities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe and ſuperſtitious ceremonies; and to carry on ſuch a complyance with the grand hereſie of Popery, as might put Papiſts in great hope, that if they were too ſtout to come to us, we would be ſo humble as to come to them.</p>
               <p>Thence it was that they bragged (when they ſaw the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion table ſet up, and railed in as an Altar, and the places of publick worſhip popiſhly painted) that our Church<note n="(q)" place="margin">See <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths</hi> pref. in anſw. to a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Charity miſtaken.</note> 
                  <hi>began to look with a new face, &amp; their walls to ſpeak a new lauguage,</hi> by the new face they meane a new draught, and by the new language, a new dialect of Popiſh conformity; and<note n="(r)" place="margin">ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>that our</hi> 39. <hi>Articles are pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, yea ambitious in ſome ſenſe to ſeem Catholick;</hi> that is (in their ſenſe) Popiſh. So that it may with good probability be collected, that the devill ſpitteth at <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> by ſo many late ſpread, though not late hatcht hereſies, with the more ſpight and rage, out of the revenge of the quarrell of Prelacie, the putting down where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65388:29"/>in reſpect of their forementioned evill dealings, he cannot but take for a great prejudice and impediment to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Kingdome; by which returne of the objection, we deſire not to put any reproach upon ſuch as were not parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with the evill deeds of their pragmaticall brethren, for to them we reſerve place for an apologeticall plea, ſo farre as their learning, piety, pains-taking, moderation and humility (wherein ſome of them are eminent) may be capable thereof.</p>
               <p>And now (deare Brethren) wee have thus joyned with you in publick profeſſion, and our engagement to the Covenant and Government of the Church, and our reſolution according to our calling and places, to ſtand for defence and promotion of both, and in oppoſition to all errour, &amp;c. contrary to them. We doubt not but you will joyn with us in unceſſant ſollicitations at the throne of grace, that God will be pleaſed to make way for fincere and affectionate entertainment of both in the hearts of the people to whom they are tendered, and that by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thereupon they may attaine thoſe happy end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (for which they were propoſed) and have been approved by the two Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes of Parliament, the venerable Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inſter,</hi> the reverend Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithfull and worthy Miniſters, and conſcientious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, both in City and Countrey. And we wiſh we could ſay ſo much, and of ſo many in both the Univerſities of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>And for the Apologeticall ſupplement we have made againſt the reproach of our preſent Reformation, we hope you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our godly and learned brethren, wil accept of as an aſſay, to doe the truth and them, as well as our ſelves, both a neceſſary and acceptable ſervice. To which we will make no further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then the ſubſcription of our names.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65388:30"/>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>IOhn Ley, <hi>for the preſent Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cher at</hi> Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ry</item>
                        <item>Thomas Langley, <hi>Miniſter a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> Middle wich</item>
                        <item>Henry Maſy, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Ofwald's <hi>in</hi> Cheſter</item>
                        <item>John Glendole, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Peters <hi>in</hi> Cheſter</item>
                        <item>Thomas Upton, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Trinity in Cheſter</item>
                        <item>William Pearetree, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Mary's <hi>in</hi> Cheſter</item>
                        <item>Benjamin Ball, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> John's <hi>in</hi> Cheſter</item>
                        <item>Hugh Burroughs, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Chriſtleton</item>
                        <item>John Marigold, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Waverton</item>
                        <item>Joſias Clark, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Tattenhall</item>
                        <item>Kichard Chapman, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Thornton <hi>in the Moores</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>George Cottingham, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Plemſtall</item>
                        <item>James Hutchinſon <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Dodleſtone</item>
                        <item>Randall Gueſt, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Poulford</item>
                        <item>William Anderton, <hi>Paſtor de</hi> Coppenball</item>
                        <item>Joſua Golborne, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Eccleſton</item>
                        <item>Randall Adams, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Walleſey</item>
                        <item>William Glegge, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Haſwall</item>
                        <item>Bryan Laſcells, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Thurſtaſton</item>
                        <item>Ralph Poole, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Berington</item>
                        <item>Samuel Marſden, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Neſton</item>
                        <item>Rob. Frecleron, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Backford</item>
                        <item>Richard Hopwood, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Burton</item>
                        <item>William Hewetſon, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Sho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>wick</item>
                        <item>Henry Hatton, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Overchurch</item>
                        <item>John Murcot, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Weſtkirby</item>
                        <item>Daniel Sunderland, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Bunbury</item>
                        <item>Nathaniel Lancaſter, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Tarperly</item>
                        <item>Sabbath Clarke, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Tarvin</item>
                        <item>John Boyer <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Barrow</item>
                        <item>Samuel Bowden, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Frodeſham</item>
                        <item>George Mainwaring, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Malpas</item>
                        <item>William Holland, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Malpas</item>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65388:31"/>
                        <item>John Ford, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Over</item>
                        <item>John Roberts, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Aldford</item>
                        <item>William Bridges, <hi>Paſtor de</hi> Farndon</item>
                        <item>Samuel Catherall, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Hanley</item>
                        <item>James Marbarry, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Davenham</item>
                        <item>Richard Fowler, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Bartomliy</item>
                        <item>Edward Burghall, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Acton</item>
                        <item>John Pemberton, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Congleton</item>
                        <item>Joſeph Cope, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Sambach</item>
                        <item>Randall Silletoe, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Lowton</item>
                        <item>Tho. Jemſon, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Presbury</item>
                        <item>James Watmough, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Bowden</item>
                        <item>Ralph Hall, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Knotsford</item>
                        <item>Ephraim Elcock, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Runckorne</item>
                        <item>John Hulme, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Great Budworth</item>
                        <item>Robert Stringer, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Macclesfield</item>
                        <item>Nicolas Stevenſon, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Alderlcy</item>
                        <item>Nehemia Northington, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Chelford</item>
                        <item>Nehemia Potte, <hi>Miniſter of</hi> Wincle</item>
                        <item>Richard Jackſon, <hi>Minister at</hi> Namptwich</item>
                        <item>Da. Ker, <hi>Minister at</hi> Audſin</item>
                        <item>Humphry Whittingham, <hi>Paſtor at</hi> Wiſtaſton</item>
                        <item>Thomas Swan, <hi>Paſtor of</hi> Baddiley</item>
                        <item>Henry Griffith, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Wrenbury</item>
                        <item>Edward Mercer, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Burldam-chappell</item>
                        <item>Henry Newcome, <hi>Miniſter at</hi> Gooſetree.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:65388:31"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation aforeſaid.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. <hi>The firſt Part,</hi> ſhewing how far the Miniſters of <hi>CHESHIRE</hi> conſent with their Brethren of the Province of <hi>LONDON;</hi> divided into 2. Sections.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. I.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> 
                           <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Autions concerning the charge of hereſie, and uſe of the word Heretick; the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of defining the one, and of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the other. <hi>Page. 2, 3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> The concurrence of the Miniſters of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> with their Brethren of the Province of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and of other Counties, in the confeſsion of Faith, exhibited by way of humble advice to the High Court of Parliament, by the Aſsembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. p. 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> And in the Presbyteriall Government, miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the people, and the evill effects of that miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, with the benefit of that Government, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by it, where it is ſet up and eſtabliſhed in a graduall ſubordination of Congregationall, Claſsicall, and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Aſsemblies. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> And in the Solemn Leagn &amp; Covenant, and ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations upon ſleighting the Covenant, without all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:65388:32"/>of conſcionable, either taking or keeping thereof. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> And againſt the Toleration of errors, hereſies, and blaſphemies, and the evill thereof, yet not all alike intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VI.</hi> Some erros more diſputable, and more probable then others, as appearing in a Scripture expreſſion; yet not to bee entertained with ſuch favourable conſtruction, as the doubtfull paſſage of Scripture ſhould be, and the reaſons why ſo. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VII.</hi> Why <hi>Luther</hi> wiſhed his own books burnt, yet when they were ſo, he burnt the Popes Law, and that Decree, by which they were ſentenced to the fire. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VIII.</hi> The high praiſe of his Commentary upon the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians,</hi> and prelation of it before many workes of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>p. 6.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IX.</hi> A blaſphemous compariſon of the Scripture. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. II.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> DIſtinction and difference to bee made betwixt error, and error, both in judgment, and in practiſe. <hi>p. 7.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> The morall or pious converſation of men, ſhould be no protection to their erroneous opinions. The lives of Hereticks, Turkes, and of ſome Epidures (in opinion) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> Errors inconfeſtent with Salvation, not to be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> How they are to be oppoſed by Miniſters, and how far by Magiſtrates. Some errors poo abſurd to be dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by Argument. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> The Zeal of the Heathen, againſt ſuch as publiſh im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious opinions, and of Chriſtians against the like. <hi>p. 9.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:65388:32"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VI.</hi> The book called the <hi>Bloody Tenet,</hi> a bloody booke, dictated by Satan, with a thirſt after the blood of the ſouls of men. <hi>p. 9.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VII. Auguſt.</hi> retracted his opinion touching the Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hereticks. <hi>p. 10.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VIII.</hi> The Ordinance of Parliament, <hi>May 2. 1648.</hi> for puniſhment of blaſphemies. <hi>p. 10, 11, &amp; 12.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IX.</hi> Divers of the Independent way, learned,<note place="margin">The Authour of the Bloody Tenet, printed 1644. See p. 9. of this Atteſta</note> godly and charitable to their godly Brethren, though Presbyterians. Yet Independency an error, and as ſome inlarge the Tenet, the Nurſe, if not the Mother of many dangerous deviati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, both from truth and piety. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>X.</hi> The Tyranny of Papiſts over the conſciences and lives of men to be abhorred. With what moderation erring Chriſtians are to be dealt with, yet without prejudice to needfull ſeverity, in caſes of importance, <hi>p. 13.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. Part, containing the reaſons why the Miniſters of <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> thus joyn with their Brethren in the Province of <hi>London,</hi> in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in the publick Profeſſion thereof. Divided into 5 Sections.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. I.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> AN advantage to be in ſociety with good men, yet that Society muſt be grounded upon reaſon. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> The firſt reaſon of this Atteſtation, taken from the juſt zeal, Chriſtians, eſpecially Miniſters, ought to bear to the glory of God. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> The error of <hi>Themiſtius</hi> holding and informing the Emperour <hi>Valens,</hi> That variety of Religions tended to the glory of God. <hi>300.</hi> Differences of opinions, among Philoſophers. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:65388:33"/>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> The Devill upon deferting of Idoll Temples, and erecting of the Chriſtian-Religion, raiſed up hereticks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Chriſtians to undermine Chriſtianity. <hi>p. 15.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> The Marcionites and Manichees, going againſt the Law loſe all intereſt in the Goſpel, the witleſs &amp; wilful op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Law, by the hereticks called <hi>Antitactae;</hi> the impiety of the book of <hi>Mans Mortality. ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VI.</hi> The zeal of <hi>Nehemiah, Hezekiah, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> worthy imitationin. <hi>p. 16, 17.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. II.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>THe ſecond reaſon of this Atteſtation, taken from the Duty of the Miniſter in</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi> Relation to their charge of Soules, endangered by hereſie, as by a Cancer, and Gangrene; the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, according to <hi>Galen. p. 17, &amp; 18.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2.</hi> Hereſie deadly, as lime mingled with milke: an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick a man of blood. <hi>p. 18.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3.</hi> The third reaſon taken from the conſideration of the ſafety and honour of the Kingdome; which are much oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and impeached by errors, hereſies. <hi>p. 18, &amp; 19.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4.</hi> The ſafety of civill ſocieties endangered by want of juſtice, and by pernicious doctrins.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5.</hi> The diſhonour of <hi>England,</hi> by abundance of Sects, aggravated by compariſon of our preſent time, and ſtate; with the precedent of <hi>England,</hi> with other Kingdoms. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6.</hi> The beſt Remedy and Apologie in reſpect of both, is publikely to profeſſe againſt them; the Parliament hath done it thrice. <hi>1.</hi> By their firſt Declaration. <hi>2.</hi> By the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for a publike faſt for the ſpreading of hereſie, <hi>March</hi> the <hi>10.</hi> And <hi>3.</hi> by their Ordinance, <hi>May 2.</hi> for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing blaſphemy's, hereſies, &amp;c. <hi>p. 19. &amp; 20.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:65388:33"/>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. III.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>A</hi> Fourth reaſon for publick profeſsion againſt hereſies, is taken from</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi> The ſedulity, ſubtilty, and pride of hereticks, as of <hi>Eunomius. p. 22.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2.</hi> Taken from the levity, and inclination of the common people to vagrant ſpeculations, who are willing to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, willfull when they are deceived. <hi>p. 23.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3.</hi> The cauſe of mens pertinacy in evill opinions: hereſie and ſpirituall frenzy, hardly cured. <hi>p. 23. &amp; 24.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4.</hi> A ſixth reaſon, taken from the Zeal of the ancient Fathers, againſt hereſies; as of the Councell of <hi>Nice, Polycarpe, Hierom,</hi> and others; though <hi>Hierom</hi> were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too ſharp againſt ſome, for their opinions on this ſide hereſie. <hi>p. 25.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5.</hi> A ſeventh reaſon, from the like Zealous oppoſition of hereſie by the reformed Churches; as by the Synod at <hi>Dort,</hi> and other godly Divines, conſenting with it againſt the Arminians. <hi>p. 25.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>6.</hi> The Zeal of King <hi>James</hi> againſt <hi>Conrad Voſtius:</hi> The ſtile of the Kings of <hi>England, DEFENDER OF THE FAITH,</hi> when firſt given them, by whom, and for what. <hi>p. 26.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>7.</hi> The Eighth reaſon taken from the care the Heathens had of their own erroneous Religions, and from their Religious obſervation of an oath. <hi>p. 26.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>8. Regulus</hi> an heroicke <hi>Roman,</hi> willingly dyed, that he might not be wilfully forſworn. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>9.</hi> How much confidence morall heathens have repoſed in an oath, and what benefit they both expected and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by conſcionable keeping of an oath. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:65388:34"/>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. IV.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1.</hi> THe Ninth reaſon from the danger both of ſinne and puniſhment, by connivence and ſilence at the wickedneſſe of others. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2.</hi> For that Chriſtians have been paſſive partakers in the puniſhment of heathens. <hi>p. 29.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>3.</hi> Politick neutrality deteſted by ingenuous moraliſts. <hi>ib.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>4.</hi> The <hi>10.</hi> reaſon taken from the good acceptance of the teſtimony to the Truth, againſt errors &amp;c. ſhewed by our reverend and godly Brethren of <hi>Scotland;</hi> who plead it to the eſtates of their Parliament, for preſervation of Peace, and prevention of War betwixt the Kingdoms. <hi>p. 29, 30.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>5.</hi> Differences betwixt Presbytenian, and Independent, not to be decided by a War. <hi>p. 30.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. V.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> THe breach of Covenant politickly pretended for the raiſing of a new War, deſtructive to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, both in the doctrinall and practicall parts of it. <hi>p. 31, 32.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> Wee ſhall gratifie our greatest enemies, and act their moſt dangerous deſignes againſt our ſelves, if wee take up a War betwixt Presbyterian and Independent. <hi>p. 33.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> Herein there is great reaſon the Independents ſhould be of the ſame mind with their Presbyterian Brethren, and ſhould be as willing as they, to maintain mutuall peace, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding difference of opinions betwixt them. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> The Papiſts ſubtilty in ſetting diſſentions among the Proteſtant party. The inſtructions given to Seminarie Prieſts to that purpoſe, by Cardinall <hi>Allen. p. 34.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> No private diſſentions ſhould withhold us from hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding together for the defence of the publick. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:65388:35"/>
               <head>A III. Part of the Atteſtation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Apology for Publication of theſe Errors, and for the Reformation in hand againſt the ſcandall of them; and of other impious and abſurd aberrations from Religion and reaſon charged upon it.</head>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. I.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> THe difference of errors ſuch, that though ſome of them need the addition of an Antidote when they are publiſhed, others do not. <hi>p. 35, 36.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> Some errors both in Philoſophie and Divinity, thought new, which have been deviſed and divulged of old. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> Reformation carried on too violently from one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream to another. <hi>p. 37.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> Errors and hereſies have abounded the more, by a kind of <hi>interregnum</hi> betwixt pulling down the Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſetting up the Presbyteriall Government. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> The Divell moſt beſtirreth himſelf in broaching and ſpreading Errors and Hereſies, when any great worke of Reformation is ſet on foot. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VI.</hi> Four remarkable tines obſervable for evidence thereof. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. II.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> THe firſt when Chriſtianity was to be ſet up, and Iudaiſm, and Paganiſm to be preached down. <hi>p. 37.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> Many impious impure and abſurd Hereſies ſet up, &amp; ſet out by Satan, to reproach the firſt Reformation. <hi>p. 38.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> As that of <hi>Simon Magus, Nicolas</hi> the Deacon of
<pb facs="tcp:65388:36"/>
                           <hi>Antioch,</hi> though of him there be oppoſite opinions of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, ſome accuſing him of fleſhly wantonneſſe, ſome excuſing him, and charging all the crime upon his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, called <hi>Nicolaitans. ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> The abominable impiety, and impurity of the <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks. p. 39.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>A medicine how made of their poyſon. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> The <hi>Adamites</hi> ridiculous Religion. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VI.</hi> Some worſhipped the Serpent, that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> and highly approved of <hi>Cain, Core,</hi> the <hi>Sodomites</hi> and <hi>Judas. p. 40.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VII.</hi> The ſinfull abſurdity of the Carpocratian hereſie. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>VIII.</hi> The <hi>Pepuſians</hi> who admitted women to all eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Miniſteries. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. III.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> THe ſecond remarkable Reformation from Popery to Proteſtancy inveſted with many groſſe, and wicked errors. <hi>p. 41.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> What they were. <hi>p. 40, 41.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> The wicked opinions and practiſes of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and Libertines in <hi>Germany. p. 42, 43.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> The witleſſe, and graceleſſe Hereſies of the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines. <hi>p. 44, 45.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>V.</hi> Among which ſome are ſuch, as our late News-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers report to the reproach of the preſent Reformation.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. IV.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> THe third conſiderable time of Reformation, was in <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> Raign, when godly Divines endeavoured
<pb facs="tcp:65388:36"/>a further conformity with other reformed churches in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline and ceremony, more different from the manner of the Church of <hi>Rome. p. 46.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2.</hi> Then did <hi>Martine Marprelate,</hi> the Browniſts, and <hi>Hacket,</hi> occaſion many reproaches againſt the Reformation. <hi>p. 47.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> Eſpecially <hi>Hacket,</hi> whoſe wild, wicked and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conceipts and ſayings, are reported out of <hi>Dr. Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> and <hi>Cambden. p. 47, 48.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>IV.</hi> Beſides theſe domeſticall diſturbers and diſgracers of the deſired Reformation, there were ſtrange and wicked Tenets brought out of <hi>Holland,</hi> the authour whereof was <hi>Henry Nicolai</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> the father of the family of Love; Of their books and tenets, what they were. <hi>p. 49, 50.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <label>SECT. V.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>I.</hi> THe fourth ſtate or time of Reformation is that of the preſent Parliament, which is oppoſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached with variety of errors, hereſies, &amp;c. as the former were.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>II.</hi> Which yet ſhould not be pleaded, to prejudice the Reformation in hand; ſince there bee many and weighty reaſons to acquit it from juſt cauſe of ſcandall. <hi>p. 50, 51, 52.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>III.</hi> The compariſon of the paucity of Sects (in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops time) and multiplicity of them (ſince their depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) obſerved by <hi>Hon. Reggus. p. 19.</hi> Anſwered. <hi>p. 52, 53.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:65388:37"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. I: after the words Errors, &amp;c. l: 12: add theſe words in a new line: I part ſhewing how far the miniſters of <hi>Cheſhire</hi> conſent with their Brethren of the Province of <hi>London</hi> divided into 2 Sections: p: 2: l: 34: dele, the: p: l: 7: for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentr: imminent: p: 8: l: 3: for lifes r: lives: ib: l: 28: for is: r: to be. ibid: l: 45: after but, add for: p: 10: l: 25: after places, add or: p: 13: in marg. add, lit: 5: l: 2: for <hi>quod</hi> r: <hi>quo:</hi> p: 14: for that, r: it, and then add theſe words in a new line, 2. Part, containing the reaſons why the Miniſters of <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhire,</hi> thus joyn with their Brethren of the Province of <hi>London,</hi> in their judgment, and the publick profeſſion thereof: divided in 5 Sections: p: 15: l: 27: for, to make, r: that the doctrine of the 3. coequall perſons is: ibid: l: 28, after <hi>Rome</hi> add for. p. 16. l. 18, dele, them. p. 17. l: 16. for wiſheth, r: wiſhed: p. 18. in marg: ad lit. g. l. 5: for <hi>vi</hi> r: <hi>ut,</hi> p. 18, l. 20, after him, add ſelf, ibid. l. 33. dele thirdly. p. 20, l. 3, for winds r. weeds, p. 22. l, 5. dele fourthly, p. 23. l. 1. dele fifthly. p, 26, l. 1, in marg. after that, add title. p, 30. l. 26, for then, r. and, p. 34, in marg. l. 2, after <hi>Neſterium</hi> r. <hi>damnas,</hi> p 37, l. 8, after fourthly add though, ibid l. 21, for fiftly r. yet, p. 40, l. 32, after make, add women, p. 41, l. 18. after divers, add miniſters, ibid. l. 34. for <hi>mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> r. <hi>Menne,</hi> p. 42, l. 13. after perſwaded, add and, &amp; dele that he was, ibid. l. 25, after him, add he, ibid. l. 26, after heads, dele hee, p. 43. l. 10, after <hi>Acts</hi> 26.11. add and, ibid. l. 16, after ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, add and, P. 51, l. 4, dele only, p. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, l. 18. for inveſted, r. infeſted, p. 53, l. 30, for Church, r. Churches.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
